[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "What is the minimum pressure required in a compression molding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 MPa",
            "b) 1 MPa",
            "c) 1.5 MPa",
            "d) 2 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Processing of thermosetting plastics is classified as, compression molding and transfer molding. The minimum pressure that is required for the complete operation of compression molding is 0.5 MPa. "
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "What is the minimum temperature required in a compression molding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 120°C",
            "b) 125°C",
            "c) 130°C",
            "d) 135°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "What is the maximum pressure required in a compression molding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35 MPa",
            "b) 40 MPa",
            "c) 45 MPa",
            "d) 50 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The maximum pressure that is required for the complete operation of compression molding is 50 MPa. "
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "What is the maximum temperature required in a compression molding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 240°C",
            "b) 245°C",
            "c) 250°C",
            "d) 255°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Processing of thermosetting plastics is classified as, compression molding and transfer molding. The maximum temperature that is required for the complete operation of compression molding is 250°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "In compression molding, the curing time does not depend on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Material",
            "b) Curing temperature",
            "c) Geometry",
            "d) Thickness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When there has to be molding done for thermosetting materials, mainly compression molding is preferred. While doing this, curing has to be done. The time needed for curing depends on the material used, geometry and thickness of the material. "
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "What is the maximum curing time required in a compression molding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 minutes",
            "b) 3 minutes",
            "c) 4 minutes",
            "d) 5 minutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The maximum curing time that is required for the complete operation of compression molding is 5 minutes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "What is the minimum curing time required in a compression molding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.4 minutes",
            "b) 0.5 minutes",
            "c) 0.6 minutes",
            "d) 0.7 minutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum curing time that is required for the complete operation of compression molding is 0.5 minutes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "What is the maximum pressure required in a transfer molding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 80 MPa",
            "b) 90 MPa",
            "c) 100 MPa",
            "d) 120 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Processing of thermosetting plastics is classified as, compression molding and transfer molding. The maximum pressure that is required for the complete operation of transfer molding is 100 MPa. "
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "What is the minimum pressure required in a transfer molding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 MPa",
            "b) 40 MPa",
            "c) 50 MPa",
            "d) 70 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum pressure that is required for the complete operation of transfer molding is 20 MPa. "
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "Which of the following types of molecular structure present in thermosetting polymers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear polymers",
            "b) Branched polymers",
            "c) Cross-linked polymers",
            "d) Network polymers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thermosetting materials are the polymeric materials that get permanent hardness once the heat is given to the material. These are the polymers which require heat and pressure to mould them into shape. These polymers cannot be re-softened once they are set and hardened by heat."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "How is the die used in injection molding cooled?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oil",
            "b) Air",
            "c) Water",
            "d) Contact with cold surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When it comes to molding of polymers in thermoplastics, injection molding process is the most common of the methods. In this method, whenever the die has to be cooled, there is water used to cool it."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "How does the piston in the clamping unit move?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydraulic energy",
            "b) Pneumatic energy",
            "c) Heat energy",
            "d) Suction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There is a clamping unit employed for holding the two halves together and for the opening and closing of the mold. A moving piston is provided which operates the power press. This piston works on hydraulic energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "Where does the granular molding material get loaded into?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Barrel",
            "b) Hopper",
            "c) Pellets",
            "d) Split"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a ram or plunger type injection molding system, the granular molding material has to be first loaded into a hopper, after which, with the help of a feeding device it gets metered out inside a cylinder."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "Which of the following material is not made by injection molding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nuts",
            "b) Tubes",
            "c) Car handles",
            "d) Electrical fittings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Injection molding is one of the most widely used method of molding among molding with polymers. There are various applications of this method such as nuts, bolts, cups, car handles, electrical fitting parts, but not tubes and rods."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "What is the minimum temperature allowed to be given to the injection molding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 120°C",
            "b) 130°C",
            "c) 140°C",
            "d) 150°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the molding process of polymers in thermoplastics, injection molding process is the most common of the methods. The minimum allowable temperature that can be given to the system is 150°C."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors is not considered in a ram type injection molding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inner pressure of material",
            "b) Outer pressure of material",
            "c) Volume of material",
            "d) Temperature of material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Among the following, the inner pressure of the material, the outer pressure of the material as well as the mold and the temperature of the material and mold are important factors to be considered. The volume of material is not counted among important factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "What is the minimum pressure allowed to be given to the injection molding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 90 MPa",
            "b) 100 MPa",
            "c) 140 MPa",
            "d) 170 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "What is the maximum temperature allowed to be given to the injection molding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300°C",
            "b) 320°C",
            "c) 350°C",
            "d) 400°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum allowable temperature that can be given to the system is 300°C, in this particular method of molding."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes of moulding is widely used for the manufacturing of bottle caps and automotive dashboards?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compression moulding",
            "b) Transfer moulding",
            "c) Injection moulding",
            "d) Jet moulding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Injection moulding is a manufacturing process which uses thermoplastic and thermosetting plastic materials to make products like bottle caps, automotive dashboard, combs etc. In this process, material is fed into a barrel of high temperature, then by mixing it is forced into a mould cavity where it solidifies and gets hardened."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Which of the following cooling systems is used in injection moulding process to increase solidification rate of components made?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air jet cooling system",
            "b) Water cooling system",
            "c) Cooling with free convection",
            "d) Cooling with fins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Injection moulding is a most common and dominant of all the other plastic processing methods. The process of injection moulding is very versatile and can produce very complex shaped components with the application of multisided moulds. In this process, even components with metal inserts can also be produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "In blow molding, to inflate soft plastic, which medium is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air",
            "b) Water",
            "c) Oil",
            "d) Alcohol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Blow molding process is typically used for the blowing process of hollow plastics. While blow molding, the plastic has to be inflated, in order to do so, air has to be blown inside with a high amount of pressure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "Which of the following plastics is not used in blow molding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Terephthalate",
            "b) Polypropylene",
            "c) Polythene",
            "d) PVC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For blowing processes, there are certain plastics only which are properly suited for the operation, while any other material might fail. Hence, for operating through blow molding process, polypropylene, polythene and PVC are used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "What is the minimum air pressure required in the blow molding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 350 kPa",
            "b) 400 kPa",
            "c) 450 kPa",
            "d) 500 kPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the blow molding process, there is some amount of pressure that has to be given to the air for blowing the bottles. The amount of pressure to be given depends on the material. The minimum pressure that can be given in this process is 400 kPa. "
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "What can be the maximum pressure to be given to plastic for blow molding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 700 kPa",
            "b) 750 kPa",
            "c) 800 kPa",
            "d) 850 kPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Air with an extreme amount of pressure, when is needed, it might mean the material is thicker and denser. The amount of pressure that can be provided depends totally on the material. The maximum pressure that can be provided in blow molding process is 800 kPa. "
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of blow molding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Injection blow molding",
            "b) Extrusion blow molding",
            "c) Multi-smaller blow molding",
            "d) Multi-larger blow molding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Blow molding basically is a process of inflation of air under pressure into the plastics inside the mold cavity. There are only three known types of blow molding, namely, injection blow molding, extrusion blow molding and multi larger blow molding. "
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "What is the minimum thickness required by the plastic for vacuum forming?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.125 mm",
            "b) 0.25 mm",
            "c) 0.375 mm",
            "d) 0.5 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vacuum forming is one of the classifications of thermoforming processes. Around its circumference, a clamp is attached or we need to know the minimum thickness. The minimum thickness that can be allowed for this operation is 0.125 mm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of blow molding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Toy bodies",
            "b) Door liners",
            "c) Bottles",
            "d) Pipes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Among the following, only door liners is not an application of blow molding process. Internal door liners are made using thermoforming process, while toy bodies, bottles and pipes are made using blow molding process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "What is the maximum thickness that can be allowed for a plastics sheet in a vacuum forming process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 mm",
            "b) 3.1 mm",
            "c) 3.2 mm",
            "d) 3.3 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vacuum forming process is one of the important processes that are employed in thermoforming processes. The maximum thickness of the plastic sheet has to be noted, as a clamp is to be fitted around the plastic sheet. The maximum allowable thickness of this plastic sheet is 3.2mm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Which of the following moulding processes is widely used for the manufacturing of plastic bottles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compression moulding",
            "b) Injection moulding",
            "c) Jet moulding",
            "d) Blow moulding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In blow moulding process, a heated tube of plastic material is situated between the two halves of mould, then the mould is closed and air or inert gas is usually blown at a pressure of 200 – 400 bars, which helps in expanding of tube outward to occupy the mould cavity. After that the part cools down to get hardened and then the part is ejected from the mould."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials is mostly used for making of thermoforming moulds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Steel",
            "b) Grey cast iron",
            "c) Aluminium",
            "d) White cast iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The blow moulding process is very fast and can produce components mainly plastic parts very fast and economically. The process can be completed by manual means or by semi-automatic or automatic machines. Blow moulding process is especially used for the production of plastic bottles."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Which of the following material is not used in extrusion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wax",
            "b) Granules",
            "c) Powder",
            "d) Pellets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Extrusion is a process of forcing plastic which is at a very high temperature, through the dies, and gets opened at a required shape. The raw materials used for extrusion with polymers contain granules, powder and thermoplastic pellets. "
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "In extrusion process, extra shearing occurs in which part of the system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Feed section",
            "b) Pumping section",
            "c) Collapse section",
            "d) Transition section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The section where an additional amount of melting and shearing occurs is called a pumping section. "
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Melting section is another name for which section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Feed section",
            "b) Transition section",
            "c) Pumping section",
            "d) Collapse section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Melting section is one of the types of extrusion in polymers. Extrusion is a process of forcing plastic which is at a very high temperature, through the dies, and gets opened at a required shape. Melting section is another name for transition section. "
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "How are extruded materials cooled?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water",
            "b) Contact with chilled surface",
            "c) Air",
            "d) Oil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: On completion of extrusion, the material is very hot and has to be cooled down. There are various agents which are used cooling these materials down, such as, air or water or its direct contact with a very cold surface. "
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an important factor of cooling in extrusion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduction in shrinkage",
            "b) Reduction in distortion",
            "c) Ease of adding colours",
            "d) Rate of cooling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are various factors of cooling, a few of them are, reduction in shrinkage, reduction in distortion and the rate of cooling too has to be considered. "
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of polymer extrusion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Door insulation seals",
            "b) Chewing gums",
            "c) Cables",
            "d) Circuit boards"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Circuit boards is not an application of polymer extrusion. Door insulation seals, chewing gums and cables are the applications of polymer extrusion."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Film extrusion process, best involves film having a thickness below what length?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.2 mm",
            "b) 0.3 mm",
            "c) 0.4 mm",
            "d) 0.5 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Extrusion of films is one of the most important processes in extrusion. For the films having a thickness below 0.5 mm, these films are best suited for extrusion and can be further applied for making various bags. "
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "In the cable extrusion process, what is the speed of product winding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 m/sec",
            "b) 50 m/sec",
            "c) 60 m/sec",
            "d) 70 m/sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For the insulation purpose, the coating of any wire or cable is one of the most vital polymer extrusion process. The wire is cooled and then it is wound to large spools at a speed of 50 meters per second. "
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "Which of the following equipment is used for controlling the temperature of polymer material in the extrusion process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermo resister",
            "b) Thermometer",
            "c) Thermocouple",
            "d) Glass tube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Extrusion is a process used for the processing of various types of thermoplastics and rubbers. The extrusion process is a simple process in which liquid or molten polymer is forced through a shaped die by applying high pressure. The pressure is basically generated by the action of screw rotation against the barrel wall in the extrusion process."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of a foundry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Captive foundry",
            "b) Jobbing foundry",
            "c) Semi Production foundry",
            "d) Auto production foundry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Foundries are classified according to their type of work and the form of constitution and structure of their organization. The foundries are hence classified into four types namely, captive foundry, jobbing foundry, semi production foundry and production foundry. "
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "What is the total capacity possessed by ferrous Indian foundries?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1,00,000 tons",
            "b) 1,50,000 tons",
            "c) 2,00,000 tons",
            "d) 2,50,000 tons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are many foundries in India. A few big foundries are located in Durgapur, Asansol, Rourkela, Bhopal and Bangalore. The total capacity possessed by Indian ferrous foundries is more than 2,50,000 tons. "
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a ferrous foundry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brass foundry",
            "b) Bronze foundry",
            "c) High alloy steel foundry",
            "d) Zinc-base foundry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Among the following, a high alloy steel foundry is a type of steel foundry and steel foundries come under ferrous foundries, while the remaining ones are non-ferrous foundries."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a metal joining process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Riveting",
            "b) Bending",
            "c) Pressing",
            "d) Brazing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Riveting, brazing, pressing, soldering, adhesive bonding and bolt-screw fastening are few of the techniques of metal joining process. But, bending is not one of them, it is a shaping process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "In an automobile engine, up to what percent of parts are manufactured by casting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 65%",
            "b) 75%",
            "c) 80%",
            "d) 90%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Casting is one of the most all round process used in manufacturing. Up to 90% of the automobile engine parts are manufactured using casting, and around 50% of the total weight of the tractor is manufactured using casting. "
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a metal removing process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grinding",
            "b) Milling",
            "c) Swaging",
            "d) Hobbing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Grinding, milling, hobbing, planning, reaming, shaping, boring, turning and broaching are a few of the techniques of metal removing process. But, swaging is not a part of them, it is a type of metal shaping process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a metal shaping process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Press forging",
            "b) Broaching",
            "c) Riveting",
            "d) Lapping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Among the following, broaching is a metal machining process or a metal removal process, riveting is a metal joining process, lapping is a surface finishing process and press forging is a shaping process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a surface finishing process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Honing",
            "b) Grinding",
            "c) Boring",
            "d) Lapping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Casting provides a great amount of freedom in terms of design. It helps in providing uniform directional properties and good vibrational properties. "
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a cast steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low alloy steel",
            "b) Magnesium alloy steel",
            "c) Carbon steel",
            "d) High alloy steel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cast steel are a further classification of foundry metals and alloys under ferrous metals and alloys, that is, having iron base. Low alloy steel, high alloy steel and carbon steel are cast steels, but not magnesium alloy. "
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Which of the following forms of iron is least malleable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Austenitic",
            "b) Pearlitic",
            "c) Ferritic",
            "d) Martensitic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Malleable irons are cast irons which are classified under iron base materials, under foundry metals and alloys. Among these phases of iron, the austenite phase of iron is measured to be showing the least amount of malleability. "
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not a cast iron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) White iron",
            "b) Compacted graphite iron",
            "c) Gray cast iron",
            "d) Pig iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Among the following, white iron, compacted cast iron and gray cast iron are different types of cast irons, but pig iron is not. It is from pig iron, that cast irons are made, by re-melting them. "
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "What is the amount of carbon present in low carbon steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less than 0.5%",
            "b) Less than 0.7%",
            "c) Less than 0.4%",
            "d) Less than 0.2%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Low carbon steel has the lowest amount of carbon mixed with iron in the alloy. The amount of carbon present in low carbon steel is less than 0.2% and that of medium carbon steel has carbon composition of about 0.2% to 0.5%."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "What is the amount of carbon present in high carbon steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) More than 0.5%",
            "b) More than 0.7%",
            "c) More than 0.4%",
            "d) More than 0.2%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: More than 0.5% amount of carbon present in high carbon steel."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Which among the following is a heavy metal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Titanium base",
            "b) Aluminium base",
            "c) Zinc base",
            "d) Magnesium base"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The given metal bases are all non-ferrous metal bases, which are classified under foundry metals and alloys. Among these, the only heavy metal is the zinc base, while all others are light metals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a light metal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Copper base",
            "b) Lead base",
            "c) Nickel base",
            "d) Magnesium base"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Magnesium base is a light metal."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "What is the amount of silicon present in cast carbon steels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.25% – 0.6%",
            "b) 0.25% – 0.8%",
            "c) 0.45% – 0.9%",
            "d) 0.45% – 0.1%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The amount of silicon that is present in terms of percentage composition is found to be 0.25% to 0.8%. Elements like silicon and manganese are added in the steel alloys for the purpose of deoxidation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "What is the amount of manganese present in cast carbon steels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5% – 1.0%",
            "b) 0.25% – 0.5%",
            "c) 0.45% – 0.8%",
            "d) 1% – 2%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 0.5% – 1.0% amount of manganese present in cast carbon steels."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "Presence of which material in a gray cast iron causes reduced ductility?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Graphite",
            "b) Aluminium",
            "c) Coke",
            "d) Zinc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Among all the types of cast irons that are manufactured, gray cast irons are most widely used. The colour of this alloy is dull gray. Gray cast iron contains graphite flakes, which are responsible for the reduced ductility and strength. "
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "What would be the tensile strength of gray cast iron of class 20?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 120 MPa",
            "b) 163 MPa",
            "c) 138 MPa",
            "d) 152 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tensile strength of gray cast iron of class 20 is 163 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "What is the tensile strength of thick gray cast iron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 71 MPa",
            "b) 83 MPa",
            "c) 95 MPa",
            "d) 107 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tensile strength of thick gray cast iron is 83 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "What is the tensile strength of thick gray cast iron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 276 MPa",
            "b) 283 MPa",
            "c) 295 MPa",
            "d) 207 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tensile strength of thick gray cast iron is 276 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Up to what mass of gray cast irons can shell molds take?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300 kg",
            "b) 400 kg",
            "c) 500 kg",
            "d) 600 kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shell molding is one of the most important processes which has also been employed for the production of gray cast irons. Gray cast irons weighing up to around 500 kg are usually processed by this method. "
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Up to what thickness can hot box process can be used for production?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 mm- 40 mm",
            "b) 30 mm- 50 mm",
            "c) 40 mm- 80 mm",
            "d) 70 mm- 100 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Green sand moldings are found to provide good amount of surface finish, but an even better quality of surface finish and accuracy of dimensions is offered by shell molding process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials cannot be used for making a core box?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminium",
            "b) Steel",
            "c) Zinc",
            "d) Cast iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When gray cast irons have to be processed, there is some amount of machining required to it, which demand high costs. But, if gray cast irons have to be shell molded, the overall cost of the product goes down, making it an economical process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "What is the temperature in a core box typically?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 120°C – 160°C",
            "b) 180°C – 260°C",
            "c) 200°C – 270°C",
            "d) 290°C – 350°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In hot box process, there is a core box employed, wherein the sand mixtures are poured along with the liquid resins, which act as binders. The thickness up to which hot box process can be used is 70 mm to 100 mm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "What should be the range of percentage of carbon (C) in iron (Fe) to be called as cast iron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1-0.5",
            "b) 0.5-1.0",
            "c) 1.0-2.0",
            "d) 2.0-5.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cast iron is the oldest ferrous material that is used for commercial purposes. It is mainly a mixture of iron (Fe) and carbon (C). It can also include materials like sulfur (S), silicon (Si), and manganese (Mn). Generally, for the cast iron, the percentage of carbon in iron is 2 to 5 percent."
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Which of the following types of iron represents purest form of iron in the manufacturing process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pig iron",
            "b) White cast iron",
            "c) Wrought iron",
            "d) Grey cast iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cast iron is first melted in furnace and then poured into the mould cavity. After cooling of cast iron in the mould it is broken out. All the excess of metal from the process, gates, runners etc are removed in a process called as fettling, which also have operations like grinding and shot blasting to produce the good surface finish of the castings."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "Which of the following types of cast iron includes black flakes of graphite in it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) White cast iron",
            "b) Grey cast iron",
            "c) Ductile cast iron",
            "d) Malleable cast iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cast iron is normally of nonmalleable and brittle nature which defines that, it is not easy to bend or stretched the casting into any shape due to low tensile strength. Cast iron parts tend to fracture by little of deformation, but cast iron has excellent compressive strength which highly required in making of structures of buildings and bridges."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "Which of the following parts are mostly manufactured by using grey cast iron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pistons",
            "b) Surgical equipment’s",
            "c) Thin sheets",
            "d) Engine blocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The purest form of iron is wrought iron which has negligible amount of carbon in it. It is highly malleable and tough material which can be used for making products by rolling or forging operation instead of casting process. It is basically obtained by melting pig iron which is also called crude iron."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Presence of which material in aluminium alloy provides ductility to the alloy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silicon",
            "b) Iron",
            "c) Copper",
            "d) Zinc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: With the presence of about 2% to 5% of copper metal in aluminium alloy aids in the increase in ductility of the alloy, that is, it becomes easy for the alloy to be stretched into wires. "
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "Which furnace is not used for heating aluminium alloys?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electric arc furnace",
            "b) Pot furnace",
            "c) Induction heating furnace",
            "d) Crucible furnace"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aluminium alloys can be melted or heated directly or indirectly by fuel firing furnace. The heating can take place in a pot furnace, induction heating furnace, a crucible furnace or a reverberatory furnace. "
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a purpose of fluxing and flushing the aluminium alloys?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Removal of dissolved hydrogen",
            "b) Removal of dissolved oxygen",
            "c) Separation of dross from melt",
            "d) Entrapment of dross"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fluxing and flushing are an important task in aluminium alloy foundries. It is done for removing the dissolved hydrogen from the melt, for separating the dross from molten metal and to entrap the dross. "
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "What is the silicon composition present in an LM-17 cast aluminium alloy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3%",
            "b) 12%",
            "c) 5.5%",
            "d) 11.5%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In an LM-1 cast aluminium alloy, silicon content is 3%. In an LM-13 cast aluminium alloy, silicon content is 12%. In an LM-8 cast aluminium alloy, silicon content is 5.5% and in an LM-17 cast aluminium alloy, the silicon content is 11.5%."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "Which gas is not used for fluxing and flushing in aluminium alloys?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Argon",
            "b) Chlorine",
            "c) Nitrogen",
            "d) Oxygen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fluxing and flushing is an operation which is done for the removal of hydrogen from the molten metal. In this process, argon gas, chlorine gas, nitrogen gas and helium gas are used as fluxes and not oxygen. "
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "Up to what length can the surface finish be achieved by green sand in aluminium alloys?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 600 micro inch",
            "b) 650 micro inch",
            "c) 700 micro inch",
            "d) 750 micro inch"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When green sand is used for molding in aluminium alloys, the surface finish can be achieved from about 300 micro inch to 650 micro inch, which is about 7500 micro mm to 16,250 micro mm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Which of the given metals is not counted among late additions in aluminium alloys?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boron",
            "b) Titanium",
            "c) Manganese",
            "d) Sodium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are certain metals which are added very late in the molten cast. By doing this, aluminium alloys get refined. A few of those metals are, boron, titanium, sodium, chromium and columbium. Manganese is added in aluminium during the operation, not late. "
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Aluminium alloys are not susceptible to which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Macro shrinkage",
            "b) Drossing",
            "c) Micro shrinkage",
            "d) Solidification shrinkage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aluminium alloys are susceptible to drossing, micro shrinkages and solidification shrinkages, but not to macro shrinkages. For the prevention of entering of dross in mold cavity, gating system is installed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "What is the general density of steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.67 g/cc",
            "b) 7.87 g/cc",
            "c) 8.77 g/cc",
            "d) 5.77 g/cc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A steel is basically a mixture of iron and carbon. The composition of iron varies according to the alloy, high alloy steels contain more amounts of carbon and low alloy steels contain less amount of carbon. The density of steels in general is found to be 7.87 g/cc."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "What is the density of copper alloys?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.67 g/cc",
            "b) 7.87 g/cc",
            "c) 8.93 g/cc",
            "d) 5.77 g/cc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A steel is a mixture of iron and carbon and copper alloys are mixtures of mainly copper and a few other materials like zinc and nickel with it. The main copper alloys can be brass and bronze. The density of copper alloys in general is found to be 8.93 g/cc."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "Which colour is obtained by copper alloys, when zinc is added to it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Red",
            "b) Blue",
            "c) Silver",
            "d) Yellow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is one of the most unusual properties of copper alloys, that on addition of different materials in them, there is a change observed in its appearance, that is, the colour of the mixture starts changing. On addition of zinc metal in copper, the colour of the mixture changes to yellow."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Which colour is obtained by copper alloys, when nickel is added to it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Red",
            "b) Blue",
            "c) Silver",
            "d) Yellow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "What amount of impurity is allowed for copper to be used in electric applications?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1%",
            "b) 0.2%",
            "c) 0.3%",
            "d) 0.4%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Copper and its alloys find themselves a variety of applications in the field of electrical and micro electrical works. For copper to be able to get used in electric appliances, the maximum impurity that can be allowed is 0.1%."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials, on adding with copper, doesn’t increase its strength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cadmium",
            "b) Silver",
            "c) Sodium",
            "d) Aluminium Oxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Copper originally does not possess a very high amount of strength. For properties of copper to be used, but with more strength, this copper needs to be mixed with certain material, which will provide it the required strength. Cadmium, silver and aluminium oxide are few of those materials which will aid in increasing its strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "What is the tensile strength of cast manganese bronze?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 490 MPa",
            "b) 759 MPa",
            "c) 676 MPa",
            "d) 324 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 759 mega pascals is the tensile strength of quenched and tempered copper-aluminium alloy. 676 MPa is the tensile strength of cold worked zinc. 324 MPa is the tensile strength of annealed zinc and 490 MPa is the tensile strength of cast manganese bronze."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "What is the tensile strength of pure annealed copper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 324 MPa",
            "b) 676 MPa",
            "c) 759 MPa",
            "d) 209 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "Which of the following parts are mostly manufactured by using copper alloys?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pistons",
            "b) Engine blocks",
            "c) Journal bearings",
            "d) Aircrafts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: No any special protective treatments are required for copper alloys against corrosion, as they have capability to protect themselves from corrosion. For the sea water applications, copper alloys are used which have high resistance to corrosion and chloride which is present in sea water in an abundant amount."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Pure magnesium melts at what temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 600°C",
            "b) 650°C",
            "c) 700°C",
            "d) 750°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The temperature at which the pure form of magnesium gets ignited by itself is 473°C, and the temperature at which magnesium in its purest form is found to melt is 650°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Which of the following metals is least used in making magnesium alloys?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminium",
            "b) Zinc",
            "c) Copper",
            "d) Manganese"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Magnesium metal in itself is not one of the strongest metals and is hence adulterated with other materials to form strong alloys. Among the following, aluminium, zinc and manganese are highly used in making magnesium alloys. "
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be the casting temperature for magnesium alloys?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 630°C",
            "b) 760°C",
            "c) 850°C",
            "d) 970°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When it comes to casting of magnesium alloys, the casting temperatures have to be kept in real control, that is, if the temperatures go too high, the metal might catch fire. The temperature range for casting magnesium alloys is 720°C to 800°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a property of a magnesium alloy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High damping capacity",
            "b) High electrical conductivity",
            "c) Good fatigue strength",
            "d) High thermal resistivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Magnesium on getting mixed with other elements starts possessing many different properties. It contains good damping capacity, good electrical conductivity and good fatigue strength, but not, thermal resistivity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "What is the color of pure magnesium metal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Red",
            "b) White",
            "c) Black",
            "d) Yellow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The purest form of magnesium is considered to be in its weakest form, and hence other elements are added in it to enhance its quality. The physical qualities too change on addition of other elements. Originally, the color of pure magnesium metal is silvery white. "
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "What should be the temperature of the mixture while alloying takes place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 550°C",
            "b) 600°C",
            "c) 650°C",
            "d) 700°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: During the mixture getting processed, first the magnesium is melted, and then zinc metal is added. Aluminum is mixed in it through stirring. While this is happening, it has to be ensured, that the complete alloying process takes place at 700°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "In magnesium alloys, what is the maximum amount of allowed aluminum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11%",
            "b) 13%",
            "c) 19%",
            "d) 24%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Magnesium alloys are basically a composition of various metals mixed with magnesium to improve its physical, chemical, mechanical and thermal properties. In this, the maximum allowable aluminum that can be added is only 11%."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "What should the temperature ideally be to remove the casting after making of magnesium alloys?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Below 450°C",
            "b) Below 300°C",
            "c) Below 350°C",
            "d) Below 300°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is always advisable that the castings should never be removed too quickly, as it might lead to distortion of the cast because it is still hot. Therefore, when the temperature of the cast is below 300°C, the magnesium alloy cast can be removed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "In sand casting of magnesium alloys, what is the amount of silica sand used in an American mix?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 80 lb",
            "b) 90 lb",
            "c) 100 lb",
            "d) 110 lb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In grain refinement process, there is another process called carbon inoculation, in which, tablets of organic compounds are used, namely hexachlorobenzene and hexachloroethane. "
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "In sand casting of magnesium alloys, what is the amount of bentonite sand used in a British mix?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 lb",
            "b) 4 lb",
            "c) 5 lb",
            "d) 6 lb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Magnesium alloys possess many desirable mechanical, physical and thermal properties, which may help in better casting processes. One of these properties is a high strength to weight ratio. "
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "Which of the following compounds can be used as an inhibitor in moulding materials for avoiding chemical reaction with magnesium alloys?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium silicate",
            "b) Water",
            "c) Hydrogen silicate",
            "d) Potassium borofluoride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In general, magnesium alloy component tends to have coarse grain structure unless some suitable procedures are taken to insure the formation of fine grains. The procedure involves superheating of molten metal to 2500 or 3000 ⁰C. And then after holding it there for a certain period of time, it cools down to the desired temperature and pouring operation takes place without any delay. "
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials are commonly used as flux in the casting process to prevent oxidation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium silicate",
            "b) Lead",
            "c) Sodium chloride",
            "d) Sodium carbonate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The flux is mixed with casting while solidification that basically reacts with a network of oxides and converts them into a powder that floats on the casting so it becomes easier to separate out that part. The whole reaction takes place is exothermic. The flux is normally used after the cleaning process which prevents progressive oxidation."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "What should be the melting point (in ⁰C) of flux used for mixing with aluminium casting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 440⁰C",
            "b) 555⁰C",
            "c) 606⁰C",
            "d) 660⁰C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sodium chloride is commonly used as flux in the casting process to prevent oxidation. Sometimes potassium fluoride is also preferred as a flux due to its excellent volatility. It not only prevents the oxidation, the other inclusions are also reduced by using flux. This process avoids metal wastage and avoids several defects formation."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "Which of the following devices is mainly used for thermal analysis of flux?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermocouple",
            "b) Thermometer",
            "c) Thermo resister",
            "d) Spiral optical tube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: After degassing process, the hydrogen does not stop coming in the casting material. This can only be controlled by using fluxes in the casting material but it is always recommended to determine the gas quantity before casting process, a device called reduced pressure gas determination equipment is then used for determining the gas content."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials is the most dominant in aero engine applications?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Iron",
            "b) Brass",
            "c) Titanium",
            "d) Copper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Titanium is a low density material which is approximately 60% of the density of steel. It is mainly strengthened by alloying and deformation methods. It is a nonmagnetic metal which has low thermal conductivity. Its coefficient of thermal expansion is generally less than that of steel and less than half that of aluminium."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods of melting is not used for melting titanium metal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Induction method",
            "b) Vacuum arc method",
            "c) Electron beam melting",
            "d) Cupola furnace melting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Titanium alloys have melting point greater than that of steels, but maximum temperatures for various applications normally range from 428 °C to approximately 540 °C. It mainly depends upon the composition and its characteristics. Titanium aluminide alloy can achieve temperature up to 760 °C for some applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "How is much amount of chromium (in percent) normally added in steel to be called as stainless steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-2 %",
            "b) 2-5 %",
            "c) 5-10%",
            "d) 10-30 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stainless steels mainly contain 10-30 % of chromium besides other elements such as carbon, manganese, silicon, sulphur etc. Chromium produces corrosion resistance property in steel, that’s why the material is known as stainless steel as no any kind of stains are occur on the surface of the steel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "Which of the following types of stainless steels contain maximum amount of chromium in it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Duplex stainless steels",
            "b) Martensitic stainless steels",
            "c) Austenitic stainless steels",
            "d) Precipitation hardenable stainless steels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Duplex stainless steels contain approximately 25 % of chromium while rest of the stainless steels contain less than that of duplex stainless steels. All the stainless steel materials contain chromium and carbon besides other elements. In production of stainless steels, controlling of carbon and chromium content should be proper."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials is required in a technique of decarburizing the molten steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calcium carbonate",
            "b) Sodium chloride",
            "c) Carbon ferrochrome",
            "d) Sodium ferrochrome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the manufacturing of stainless steel, both chromium and carbon can be oxidized due to decarburization of molten casting. Carbon oxidation in comparing with chromium oxidation may occur at temperature above 1220 ⁰C in the pure state conditions. But experimentally, carbon oxidation can occur at temperature above 1800 ⁰C than that of chromium."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "Which of the following gases is used in the method of recirculation degassing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrogen",
            "b) Nitrogen",
            "c) Argon",
            "d) Oxygen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During production of casting products, gases such as oxygen, hydrogen and nitrogen get dissolved in the casting. The term degassing is employed for the removal of these gases from the casting melt. Dissolved oxygen from molten casting cannot be extract as molecular oxygen, removing of oxygen from melt is called as de-oxidation."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "Which of the following formulas is used for determining the circulation rate (R) in recirculation degassing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R = 1.42*103*Q1/3*d1/3*{ln(P1/P2)}",
            "b) R = 2.42*103*Q1/3*d1/3*{ln(P1/P2)}",
            "c) R = 5.14*103*Q1/3*d1/3*{ln(P1/P2)}",
            "d) R = 7.42*103*Q1/3*d1/3*{ln(P1/P2)}"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During solidification of molten casting in mould cavity, excess of nitrogen is extracted from the melt which can cause blow holes and embrittlement of heat affected zone of casting component. So, it is very necessary to remove nitrogen from the melt to produce castings of desired quality and defects free."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "What is the pH level of leachate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-3",
            "b) 3-6",
            "c) 6-9",
            "d) 9-12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The pH level of the leachate has the requirement to be somewhere in between 6 to 9 on the pH scale. This would indicate that, the substance leachate is a basic substance. "
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "From what is furfural alcohol derived?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon dioxide",
            "b) Waste water",
            "c) Waste vegetables",
            "d) Sulphur dioxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Furfural alcohol (FA) gets derived from vegetable matter which is wasted, by processing it under pressure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "What is the source of fuel of the boiler in process energy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Waste from FA processing",
            "b) Waste from CO2 production",
            "c) Waste from SO2 production",
            "d) Waste from NO2 production"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The waste that is achieved after processing of furfural alcohol is used to fuel the boiler in the process energy. "
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "What is the formaldehyde level in phenolic ester in mixing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less than 0.2 parts per million",
            "b) Less than 0.3 parts per million",
            "c) Less than 0.4 parts per million",
            "d) Less than 0.5 parts per million"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: On mixing and even on casting, in the phenolic esters, the formaldehyde levels are found to be exceedingly low. "
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "What is the formaldehyde level in phenolic ester in casting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less than 0.2ppm",
            "b) Less than 0.3ppm",
            "c) Less than 0.4ppm",
            "d) Less than 0.5ppm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "What is the phenol level in phenolic ester in casting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less than 2ppm",
            "b) Less than 3ppm",
            "c) Less than 4ppm",
            "d) Less than 5ppm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "What should the total percentage of re-use of sand in reclamation be?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 80%",
            "b) 85%",
            "c) 90%",
            "d) 95%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "Potassium hydroxide melts at what temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 260°C",
            "b) 360°C",
            "c) 460°C",
            "d) 560°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There is some amount of threat which is faced by the phenolic-ester compounds. This threat causes a kind of limitation to the reclamation. Ideally, the total percentage should be 95%."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "Potassium hydroxide boils at what temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1260°C",
            "b) 1320°C",
            "c) 1840°C",
            "d) 2560°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Potassium hydroxide is known to have its melting point at a temperature of 360°C, but it is known to have a very high boiling point of 1320°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an advantage of high volume core production?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Durability",
            "b) High strength",
            "c) Low cost",
            "d) Cures low volume production"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The very basic requirements of high volume core production is, low cost and fast manufacturing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "High volume mould production is done using which sand?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Green sand",
            "b) Dry sand",
            "c) Loam sand",
            "d) Sharp sand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When it comes to the production of high volume core productions, the cost essentially should be low. High volume mould production is done using green sand only. "
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage in low volume core production?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High production",
            "b) Consistency",
            "c) Mould rigidity",
            "d) Hardenability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In low volume core production, it offers high rate of production, better consistency and mould rigidity, but not hardenability. "
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of moderate to high volume aluminium castings?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Growth in low pressure",
            "b) Flexibility",
            "c) Low cost",
            "d) Low brittleness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In moderate to high volume aluminium castings, low pressure growth, flexibility and lower costs is an advantage, but not low brittleness. "
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "What does LPS stand for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Limited Production Sand casting",
            "b) Low Pressure System",
            "c) Limited Production System",
            "d) Low Pressure Sand casting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: LPS stands for Low Pressure Sand Casting. The growth in LPS in mainly found to be used only in for the cylindrical blocks and heads. "
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "What is mixed with calcium hydroxide on sand for CO2 cured polyacrylate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium polyacrylate",
            "b) Calcium polyacrylate",
            "c) Aluminium polyacrylate",
            "d) Iron polyacrylate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to the reaction, sodium polyacrylate is mixed with calcium hydroxide (CaOH2) on sand and is later cured with carbon dioxide gas. "
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "In Amine cured phenolic urethane, what is used as the catalyzing reagent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Primary amine",
            "b) Secondary amine",
            "c) Tertiary amine",
            "d) Nitrogen dioxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In amine cured phenolic urethane, a tertiary vaporized amine is used as a catalyst and is therefore, used for the catalyzation of the reaction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "What reacts with polyether phenolic resin to give polyurethane structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diphenyl methane diisocynate",
            "b) Triphenyl ethane diisocynate",
            "c) Diphenyl ethane diisocynate",
            "d) Triphenyl methane diisocynate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In amine cured phenolic urethane, a tertiary vaporized amine is used to catalyze the reaction between polyether phenolic resin and Diphenyl methane diisocynate to give out polyurethane structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "In Ester cured alkaline phenolic, what is used as a coreactant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A phenol",
            "b) A ketone",
            "c) An ester",
            "d) An aldehyde"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Ester cured alkaline phenolic, there is an ester called methyl formate, which is usually used as a coreactant. "
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "Which of the following is produced by Novalak – acid system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ketone",
            "b) Carboxylic acid",
            "c) Ester",
            "d) Aldehyde"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The novalak – acid system produces formaldehyde, which by the name suggests is an aldehyde and methanol while production of cores. "
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "The novalak – acid system needs what temperature conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15°C – 25°C",
            "b) 25°C – 35°C",
            "c) 35°C – 45°C",
            "d) 45°C – 55°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The novalak – acid system needs to be operated in between the temperature range of 35°C – 45°C. When this system gets operated in these temperature ranges, it is observed to yield best results. "
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a casting performance of phenolic – urethane cores?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Moderate hot strength",
            "b) Good hardenability",
            "c) Surface finish",
            "d) Low nitrogen level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Under casting performance of phenolic – urethane cores, having good hardenability does not come under it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "In the tem tech thermal sand reclamation system, how many fluidized beds are used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the tem tech thermal reclamation system, a fluidized bed plays an important role in the sand reclamation system. There are in total two fluidized beds that are used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "In the tem tech thermal sand reclamation system, the recirculating air ensures what?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Even pressure drop",
            "b) Even temperature drop",
            "c) Even volume drop",
            "d) Even loss of mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In tem tech thermal sand reclamation system, the recirculating air ensures an even pressure drop at all its orifices. "
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "What is the heat source of fluidized bed in tem tech thermal sand reclamation system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flame heating",
            "b) Ultraviolet heating",
            "c) Infrared heating",
            "d) Conduction heating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In tem tech thermal sand reclamation system, overall there are two beds involved in it and in them, shortwave infrared emitters are used in the beds. "
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "In tem tech thermal sand reclamation system, in the infrared heating system, which material is used in the beds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Copper",
            "b) Iron",
            "c) Silver",
            "d) Tungsten"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In tem tech thermal sand reclamation system, in the heating process by shortwave infrared emitters, tungsten elements are used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "What is the maximum working temperature in a fluidized bed in tem tech thermal sand reclamation system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000°C",
            "b) 2000°C",
            "c) 3000°C",
            "d) 4000°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In tem tech working system, there are two fluidized beds involved. The maximum working temperature in a fluidized bed in a tem tech thermal sand reclamation system is 2000°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "The infrared radiation passes through what before entering into the fluidized bed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prism",
            "b) Concave lens",
            "c) Quartz",
            "d) Convex lens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the tem tech thermal sand reclamation system, the infrared radiation passes through a quartz sleeve before entering the fluidized bed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "Up to what accuracy can the temperature of the bed be controlled in tem tech thermal sand reclamation system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ± 1%",
            "b) ± 2%",
            "c) ± 3%",
            "d) ± 4%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The temperature of the bed can be controlled to an accuracy of ± 2%, in tem tech thermal sand reclamation system. These fluidized beds essentially need a very accurate temperature control. "
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "In tem tech thermal sand reclamation system, what is the maximum current temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 600°C",
            "b) 700°C",
            "c) 800°C",
            "d) 900°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In tem tech thermal sand reclamation system, a high amount of temperature has to be maintained. The maximum current temperature is 800°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "In tem tech thermal sand reclamation system, how much is the energy conversion efficiency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 75%",
            "b) 80%",
            "c) 85%",
            "d) 90%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In tem tech thermal sand reclamation system, it is observed that the energy that is used gets reused and by other methods, the efficiency is taken up to great heights. There is a high energy conversion efficiency of 85%."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "With an increase in volume of air passed, what change is seen in the permeable number?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) No change occurs",
            "d) No relation among the two"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: With an increase in the volume of air passed, there is an increase in the permeable number, since the two have a direct relation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "With an increase in height of the specimen, what change is seen in the permeable number?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) No change occurs",
            "d) No relation among the two"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: With an increase in the height of the specimen, there is an increase in the permeable number, since the two have a direct relation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "With an increase in volume of air passed, what change is seen in the air pressure measurement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) No change occurs",
            "d) No relation among the two"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "With an increase in the height of the specimen, what change is seen in the air pressure measurement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) No change occurs",
            "d) No relation among the two"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "With an increase in area of the specimen, what change is seen in the permeability number?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) No change occurs",
            "d) No relation among the two"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: With an increase in the area of the specimen, there is a decrease in the permeability number, since the two have an inverse relation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "With an increase in air pressure measurement of the specimen, what change is seen in the permeability number?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) No change occurs",
            "d) No relation between the two"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: With an increase in the air pressure measurement of the specimen, there is a decrease in the permeability number, since the two have an inverse relation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "With an increase in air pressure measurement of the specimen, what change is seen in the air pressure measurement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) No change occurs",
            "d) No relation between the two"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "For baking standard core sand, the specimen needs to be heated at what temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 800°F",
            "b) 900°F",
            "c) 1000°F",
            "d) 1100°F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The core sand has to be baked first and brought to a comparatively high temperature. For baking standard core sand, the specimen needs to be heated at about 1000°F and above it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "For how long is a specimen heated in a standard core above 1000°F?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8-10 minutes",
            "b) 10-12 minutes",
            "c) 12-14 minutes",
            "d) 14-16 minutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The core sand has to be baked first and brought to a comparatively high temperature.  A standard core sand bake has to be heated above 1000°F for about 10 to 12 minutes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "Which of the following furnaces is the primary method for melting the cast iron metal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electric arc furnace",
            "b) Rotary furnace",
            "c) Cupola furnace",
            "d) Induction furnace"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cupola furnace is a furnace which is a primary method for melting the cast iron metal in the iron foundries. The cupola furnace has many unique features which are responsible for its widespread use as a melting unit. Cupola furnace is basically used for melting the scrap material or pig iron for production of several cast irons. It is also used for producing nodular and malleable cast irons."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Which of the following furnaces is mainly used for re-melting the steel metal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blast furnace",
            "b) Electric arc furnace",
            "c) Rotary furnace",
            "d) Cupola furnace"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In cupola melting furnace, a typical water cooled vertical cylinder is used which is generally lined with refractory material. The charge is introduced into the furnace through an opening half way up the vertical shaft. The charge mainly includes alternate layers of the material to be melted, flux and coke fuel."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "Which of the following cannot be operated through cupola furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cast irons",
            "b) Copper alloys",
            "c) Bronze",
            "d) Zinc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Among the following, zinc cannot be operated through cupola furnace, whereas the irons, copper base alloys and some kinds of bronzes are operated using a cupola furnace. "
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "Which instrument is attached at the top of cupola?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air blast",
            "b) Coke bed",
            "c) Wind box",
            "d) Spark arrester"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A spark arrester is positioned at the top of the cupola furnace, below which starts the stack zone, or the cupola furnace is open at the top. "
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "What should the height of a cupola furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5m",
            "b) 6m",
            "c) 7m",
            "d) 8m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The height of a cupola furnace commonly about 6m, whereas the cupolettes have a height of approximately 2.5m to 4m. There is a spark arrester attached to the top of the cupola. "
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "The bottom of the cupola is made up of which material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pig iron",
            "b) Cast iron",
            "c) White iron",
            "d) Grey iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The bottom being the legs of the cupola are made up of cast irons, also the doors for bottom opening of cupola are made of cast iron only. "
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "The volume of air passing in cupola is calculated using which device?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Area meter",
            "b) Surface meter",
            "c) Volume meter",
            "d) Pressure meter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The air flows in the cupola, passing through the combustion zone. This volume of air can be calculated using a device called as Volume meter. "
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "What is the maximum capacity of a cupolette?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.25 ton",
            "b) 0.5 ton",
            "c) 0.75 ton",
            "d) 1 ton"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Small cupolas are called as cupolettes. The capacity of a cupolette ranges from 0.5 ton to 1 ton. These cupoletes have a height of about 4.5 meters to 6 meters. "
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "What is the purpose of auxiliary tuyeres?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Raise solidification efficiency",
            "b) Drop solidification efficiency",
            "c) Raise melting efficiency",
            "d) Drop melting efficiency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cupola does not have a specific time duration of the operation. Hence, there is no uniform quality in the production of metal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "For how much time is the cupola fired before pouring?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 hours",
            "b) 3 hours",
            "c) 4 hours",
            "d) 5 hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Auxiliary tuyeres are basically used for providing to increase melting efficiency. They are fitted in one or more number of rows. "
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "Where is the cupola situated above tuyeres for superheating, combustion or oxidizing zone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15cm to 30cm",
            "b) 25cm to 40cm",
            "c) 35cm to 50cm",
            "d) 45cm to 60cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For superheating, combustion or oxidizing zone, the cupola is generally situated at the top, approximately 15cm to 30cm above the tuyeres. "
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "What is contained inside the well of cupola?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Molten iron",
            "b) Solid iron",
            "c) Molten steel",
            "d) Solid steel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Inside the well of a cupola, there is molten iron collected. The well is positioned in between of bottom of tuyeres and tapered ram sand bottom. "
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not considered under metal charge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Steel scrap",
            "b) Zinc scrap",
            "c) Cast iron scrap",
            "d) Pig iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Among the following, metal charge is found to consist of steel scrap, cast iron scrap and pig iron, but not zinc scrap. "
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "What is the amount of silica used in a slag?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20% to 30%",
            "b) 30% to 40%",
            "c) 40% to 50%",
            "d) 50% to 60%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Slag is known to be acidic in nature and it is found to have some amount of silica content in terms of percentage composition of about 40% to 50%."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "In the formation of carbon dioxide, what should the temperature of coke be?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 55°F",
            "b) 60°F",
            "c) 65°F",
            "d) 70°F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Among exothermic reactions, the production of carbon dioxide is one of the reactions. In this reaction, coke is used as a source of carbon. The temperature of coke should be 60°F. "
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "What is the range of efficiency of cupola?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20% to 40%",
            "b) 30% to 50%",
            "c) 40% to 60%",
            "d) 50% to 70%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The efficiency of cupola is decided by factors like heat used in preheating, heat used in coke, heat used in oxidation and heat in the air blast. The efficiency of a cupola varies from 30% to 50%."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "How much heat is produced in the formation of Carbon dioxide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 13269 BTU",
            "b) 2910 BTU",
            "c) 14452 BTU",
            "d) 6723 BTU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The efficiency of cupola depends on the heat used in preheating, heat used in coke, oxidation heat and also, heat in the air blast. "
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "In the reducing zone, during the endo-thermic reaction, what is the amount of heat absorbed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 13269 BTU",
            "b) 2910 BTU",
            "c) 14452 BTU",
            "d) 6723 BTU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the production of carbon dioxide, which is an exothermic reaction, a total of 14452 BTU of heat is released at every round of carbon. The temperature of coke for this should be 60°F. "
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "Given: cupola diameter = 65cm, Height of groove = 135cm, coke density = 490kg/m3. Find mass of bed charge.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 234.7 kg",
            "b) 219.5 kg",
            "c) 209.5 kg",
            "d) 216.5 kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to the question, d = 65cm = 0.65m, h = 135cm = 1.35m, w = 490 kg/m3. Therefore, according to the formula, W = π/4 x d2 x h x w => W = π/4 x 0.652 x 1.35 x 490 => W = 219.5 kg. "
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "Given: cupola diameter = 35cm, mass of bed charge = 300kg, coke density = 505kg/m3. Find height of groove.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.1 m",
            "b) 5.8 m",
            "c) 3.6 m",
            "d) 7.2 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In this question, d = 35cm = 0.35m, w = 505 kg/m3, W = 300kg. Therefore, according to the formula, W = π/4 x d2 x h x w, => h= 300 / (π/4 x 0.352 x 505) => h = 6.1m. "
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "Given: cupola diameter = 45cm, mass of bed charge = 325kg, height of groove = 6.5m. Find coke density.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 314.38 kg/m3",
            "b) 309.54 kg/m3",
            "c) 193.92 kg/m3",
            "d) 340.57 kg/m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Here, d = 45cm = 0.45m, W = 325kg, height of groove, h = 6.5m. Therefore, according to the formula, W = π/4 x d2 x h x w, => w= 325 / (π/4 x 0.452 x 325 x 6.5) => w = 314.38 kg/m3."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "What is the minimum efficiency, in general of a cupola?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15%",
            "b) 30%",
            "c) 25%",
            "d) 35%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum efficiency of a cupola is 30%, and that, the maximum efficiency is 50%. Hence, the efficiency ranges from 30 to 50% only. "
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Given: cupola diameter = 50cm, Height of groove = 155cm, coke density = 480kg/m3. Find mass of bed charge.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 146 kg",
            "b) 148 kg",
            "c) 156 kg",
            "d) 164 kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Here, d = 50cm = 0.5m, h = 155cm = 1.55m, w = 480 kg/m3. Therefore, according to the formula, W = π/4 x d2 x h x w, => W = π/4 x 0.52 x 1.55 x 480 => W = 146.08 kg. "
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Given: cupola diameter = 30cm, mass of bed charge = 270kg, coke density = 545kg/m3. Find height of groove.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 m",
            "b) 5 m",
            "c) 3 m",
            "d) 7 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Here, d = 30cm = 0.3m, w = 545 kg/m3, W = 270kg. Therefore, according to the formula, W = π/4 x d2 x h x w, => h= 270 / (π/4 x 0.32 x 545) => h = 7.008m. "
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "The weight of the bed charge does not depend on which of the following factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diameter of cupola",
            "b) Height of groove",
            "c) Type of metal used",
            "d) Coke weight density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to the formula, W = π/4 x d2 x h x w, the height of the groove is inversely proportional to the diameter of the cupola, that is, with an increase in the height there is a decrease in the diameter of the cupola. "
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Given: cupola diameter = 53cm, mass of bed charge = 465kg, height of groove = 7.2m. Find coke density.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 372.72 kg/m3",
            "b) 292.73 kg/m3",
            "c) 223.62 kg/m3",
            "d) 390.57 kg/m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The weight of the bed charge depends only on the diameter of the cupola, height of the groove and the coke weight density. It does not depend on the type of metal used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "What mass of oxygen is required for burning 1 kg of iron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.12 kg",
            "b) 2.67 kg",
            "c) 2.35 kg",
            "d) 1.92 kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Oxygen is the primary requirement for the process of burning to take place. For the burning of a metal such as iron, a high amount of oxygen will be needed. The mass of oxygen required for burning iron is 2.67 kg. "
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "What volume of oxygen is required for burning 1 kg of carbon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7.67 m3",
            "b) 9.89 m3",
            "c) 8.98 m3",
            "d) 6.67 m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "Carbon pickup does not depend on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size of coke",
            "b) Height of coke bed",
            "c) Cupola temperature",
            "d) Cupola diameter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Magnitude of carbon pickup depends on various factors such as the presence of original carbon content, size of the coke, height of the coke bed, temperature of cupola and a few more, but it does not depend on the diameter of the cupola. "
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "In the iron-iron carbide diagram, what is the carbon percentage by weight at eutectic point?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.8%",
            "b) 3%",
            "c) 4.3%",
            "d) 6.67%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the iron iron-carbide equilibrium diagram, the eutectic point is achieved at a temperature of 1147°C. At this point, the percentage amount of carbon is 4.3% by weight. "
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "In the iron-iron carbide diagram, what is the carbon percentage by weight at eutectoid point?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.8%",
            "b) 0.18%",
            "c) 4.3%",
            "d) 6.67%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "At what temperature, in the Fe-Fe3C diagram, does the peritectic region occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1400°C",
            "b) 1423°C",
            "c) 1492°C",
            "d) 1539°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the iron – iron carbide diagram, or the Fe-Fe3C equilibrium diagram, the peritectic transformation occurs at a very high temperature. The temperature point of peritectic reaction takes place is 1492°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "In the iron-iron carbide diagram, what is the carbon percentage by weight in the peritectic region?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.8%",
            "b) 0.18%",
            "c) 4.3%",
            "d) 6.67%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Carbon picks up can be of what order?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 15%",
            "c) 20%",
            "d) 25%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In carbon pick up, there is an increase in the carbon content because of absorption from coke, but there is a reduction also, because of oxidation. The order of carbon pick up can be of 15%."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "During metallurgical control, what is the amount of manganese that is lost?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5%",
            "b) 10%",
            "c) 15%",
            "d) 20%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: During metallurgical control, the amount of manganese lost is about 15%. This loss takes place because of the presence of oxygen, that is, an oxidation reaction takes place. "
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "What is the amount of pig iron in a cupola charge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10% – 20%",
            "b) 10% – 30%",
            "c) 30% – 40%",
            "d) 20% – 45%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The amount of pig iron present inside a cupola charge varies from 10% to 30%, where the exact amount depends upon the type of iron that is used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "How much steel scrap is present in refined irons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) More than 25%",
            "b) More than 60%",
            "c) More than 50%",
            "d) More than 95%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Refined irons are considered to be the second best source of high carbon material. The steel scrap which is present in refined irons is a little more than 50%."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "What is the main source of high carbon steel material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pig iron",
            "b) Cast iron",
            "c) White iron",
            "d) Steel scrap"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Steel scrap is a big source for high carbon steel materials, but is considered as the second biggest source. The main source for high carbon steel materials is pig iron. "
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "According to the UK standards, in general, what is the diameter of the iron bar which is used in iron castings?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18mm",
            "b) 12mm",
            "c) 30mm",
            "d) 43mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "What is the tensile strength of grade 220 iron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 220 Dyne/mm2",
            "b) 220 N/m2",
            "c) 220 N/mm2",
            "d) 220 Dyne/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to the standards of UK, the castings are made in a specified grade of iron. Hence, iron having a grade of 220, is equivalent to iron having a tensile strength of 220 N/mm2. "
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "The sulphur content in acid-cupola operation does not depend on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quantity of coke",
            "b) Slag basicity",
            "c) Tensile strength of the steel",
            "d) Quantity of steel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the acid-cupola reaction, the sulphur content is always increased. This increase in the sulphur content depends on quantity of coke, quantity of steel, the slag basicity, but not the tensile strength of steel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "What should be the lowest sulphur pick-up in the acid-cupola reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 13%",
            "c) 18%",
            "d) 21%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There is no such method in existence which will be able to tell us the amount of sulphur pick-up. But, the lowest amount of sulphur pick-up in acid-cupola reaction should not be more than 10%."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "What should be the highest sulphur pick-up in the acid-cupola reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 90%",
            "b) 63%",
            "c) 68%",
            "d) 51%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There is no such way by which one may be able to identify the amount of sulphur pick-up. But, the highest amount of sulphur pick-up in acid-cupola reaction should not be more than 80% to 90%."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Using what is the lining of the reverberatory furnace done?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acid",
            "b) Base",
            "c) Water",
            "d) Salt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The air furnace or the reverberatory furnace, is an acid-lined reverberatory furnace. This furnace can be used for the manufacture of malleable iron and gray iron castings. "
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "Which coal is used as a fuel in an air furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lignite",
            "b) Bituminous",
            "c) Anthracite",
            "d) Peat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the air furnace or the reverberatory furnace, a pulverized bituminous lump coal is used as a fuel. If not a bituminous coal, oils are used for the same purpose. "
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "What is the minimum capacity of an air furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 tons",
            "b) 7 tons",
            "c) 9 tons",
            "d) 11 tons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Reverberatory furnace is used for the production of malleable iron and gray iron castings. The minimum capacity of an air furnace or a reverberatory furnace is around 5 tons. "
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "What is the maximum capacity of an air furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35 tons",
            "b) 70 tons",
            "c) 19 tons",
            "d) 50 tons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "Where was the rotary melting furnace originated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Germany",
            "b) Italy",
            "c) U.S.A",
            "d) England"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The concept of the rotary melting furnace was first developed in Germany, and later because of its success, was adopted by the U.S.A and other countries of Europe. "
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "What is the shape of a rotary melting furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spherical",
            "b) Cylindrical",
            "c) Cuboidal",
            "d) Hemi-spherical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rotary melting furnace is a cylindrical shell made up of steel shell. The rotary melting furnace is used for rotating or rocking purposes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "What is the speed of rotation of a rotary melting furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 rpm",
            "b) 1 rpm",
            "c) 2 rpm",
            "d) 3 rpm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rotary melting furnace is used for rotating and rocking purposes. This furnace makes a complete rotation about itself every minute, hence the speed of rotation of a rotary melting furnace is 1 rpm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "After how many heats, should the refractory lining be renewed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50-100",
            "b) 100-200",
            "c) 200-300",
            "d) 300-400"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The refractory lining must be renewed, as the constant heating processes may cause it to damage. After approximately, 200 to 300 heats, the refractory lining should be renewed for a smooth operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "The impurities are burnt from which material in an open hearth furnace to produce steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cast iron",
            "b) Gray iron",
            "c) Pig iron",
            "d) Copper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The materials such as high carbon content or other impurities which are present inside the pig iron are burnt in order to obtain steel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "Open hearth process did not allow the steel to be in contact with which gas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrogen",
            "b) Helium",
            "c) Carbon dioxide",
            "d) Neon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The contact of steel with the nitrogen gas causes the steel to become brittle. This was one of the difficulties which was later overcome by open hearth furnace. "
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "What is the minimum capacity of an open hearth furnace in steel foundries?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 tons",
            "b) 4 tons",
            "c) 6 tons",
            "d) 3 tons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Open hearth process was primarily used only for steel making, it was later brought to use in steel foundries. The minimum capacity of open hearth furnace in steel foundries is 5 tons. "
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not charged in the open hearth furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scrap metal",
            "b) Flux",
            "c) Pig iron",
            "d) White iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In an open hearth furnace, the scrap metal, flux and the pig iron are charged through the charging doors. But, white iron is not charged into the open hearth furnace. "
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "What is the maximum capacity of an open hearth furnace in steel foundries?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 250 tons",
            "b) 100 tons",
            "c) 160 tons",
            "d) 130 tons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "Which material is applied to the hearth if the process is acidic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silica",
            "b) Dolomite",
            "c) Silicon monoxide",
            "d) Xenon di fluoride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In an open hearth furnace, there is a large basin which is called as hearth furnace. If the operation is going to be acidic, there is a lining of silica provided to the hearth. "
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not used as a fuel in an open hearth furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atomised oil",
            "b) Natural gas",
            "c) Peat",
            "d) Producer gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Only gaseous fuels are used for the burning process in an open hearth furnace. Peat is a very basic form of coal and cannot be used as a fuel here. "
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Which material is applied to the hearth if the process is basic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silica",
            "b) Dolomite",
            "c) Silicon monoxide",
            "d) Xenon di fluoride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The open hearth furnace had this as one of its limitations, that the process was time consuming. It took more time than basic oxygen furnace and electric arc furnace. "
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Up to what temperature can molten steels be produced in a side blown converter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2300°F",
            "b) 980°F",
            "c) 1350°F",
            "d) 3300°F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Here, the question mark is representing the outer shell of the converter. Inside the shell, then lies the refractory lining. "
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "Which of the following material is used in converters for making steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) White iron",
            "b) Gray iron",
            "c) Cast iron",
            "d) Copper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "Among the following, production through which material is not possible in a crucible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glass",
            "b) Metal",
            "c) Pigment",
            "d) Oils"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Crucibles are known for operating under high temperature conditions. These crucibles can be employed for the production of glass, metal and pigment, but not oils. "
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Which of the following metals or alloys cannot be used for making crucibles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nickel",
            "b) Zirconium",
            "c) Mercury",
            "d) Platinum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the making of crucibles, nickel and zirconium have been employed in the recent times. Platinum had been used for this purpose in the earlier times, owing to its inertness, but mercury cannot be used for making it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "The crucible process is used for production of which material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pig iron",
            "b) Cast iron",
            "c) Tool steel",
            "d) Gray iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The crucible process is used for the production of tool steel. Hammered iron which had rich carbon content in it was first used for producing tool steel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a property of a crucible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Retention of thermal conductivity",
            "b) Resistance to chemical attack",
            "c) Retention of electrical conductivity",
            "d) Resistance to erosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is very necessary for the crucible to have retention of thermal conductivity, to possess resistance to chemical attacks and to erosion. But, there is no need for retention of electrical conductivity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "What is the maximum pressure which the isostatic presses can take for making crucibles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 890 atm",
            "b) 1270 atm",
            "c) 1000 atm",
            "d) 1100 atm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Isostatic presses are one of the most advanced methods of making a crucible. For forming, these presses can work up to a pressure of 1000 atmospheres. "
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not hold valid for an isostatic press?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Consistent mixture",
            "b) High pressure operation",
            "c) High density of product",
            "d) Wet mix used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An isostatic press is considered to be one of the most advanced methods of making a crucible. The entire operation is at high pressure conditions. The mixture used is consistent, because of which the product formed has high density. But the mixture that is taken, is completely dry. "
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "Which of the following cannot be counted among the advantages of a crucible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uniform heating",
            "b) Low flexibility",
            "c) Low installation cost",
            "d) No contamination of charge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Melting various materials through crucibles is an old process. This process has the advantage of uniform heating and no contamination of charge by the product obtained from combustion. The operation is inexpensive, and the flexibility is high. "
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a raw material for making a crucible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clay",
            "b) Wax",
            "c) Graphite",
            "d) Silicon carbide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Production of crucibles is a very inexpensive process. It does not include much capital and the installation costs are also not very high. "
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "Which of the following furnaces is not the type of crucible furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pit furnace",
            "b) Pot furnace",
            "c) Oil fired tilting furnace",
            "d) Stack furnace"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pit furnace, pot furnace and oil fired tilting furnace are the types of crucible furnace, but stack furnace is different furnace which is a modified reverberatory furnace where its efficiency is improved by better sealing of the furnace and flue gases are mainly used for preheating the charge materials. "
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the maximum temperature limit of the electric arc furnaces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1200 ⁰C",
            "b) 1400 ⁰C",
            "c) 1600 ⁰C",
            "d) 1800 ⁰C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The electric arc furnaces can be defined as the furnaces in which charged materials are heated by the application of an electric arc. In general, these furnaces exist in all the sizes, from the smallest to the largest one having capacity of nearly about 400 tons. The electric arc furnaces can achieve temperatures up to 1800 ⁰C."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes is known for pouring of molten metal by tilting the furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Necking",
            "b) Drawing",
            "c) Tapping",
            "d) Finning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The electric arc furnaces are widely used for making steel metal, it basically consists of a water cooled roof which shapes like a section of a sphere. These furnaces also include graphite electrodes which normally enter into the furnace through the roof which can be refractory lined or water cooled."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the primary benefit of using the electric furnaces for melting the metals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High productivity",
            "b) Better quality of materials",
            "c) High strength of metals",
            "d) Less maintenance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An electric furnace mainly has three electrodes which are made round in section, and typically in segments with threaded couplings, so that new segments can be added during wearing of electrodes. Then the charged material is heated by the passing of current through the charge and the radiant energy which is developed by the arc."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "Which material is used for making the roof of an acid lined furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silica",
            "b) Dolomite",
            "c) Magnesite",
            "d) Carbon tetrachloride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A very heavy steel shell is equipped in making the roof, with the help of refractory bricks. To this, silica is added when the furnace is acid lined. "
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "Which material is used for making the roof of an acid lined furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silica",
            "b) Hydrogen peroxide",
            "c) Carbon tetrachloride",
            "d) Magnesite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "What is the minimum transformer power supply needed by the direct arc furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 600 kVA",
            "b) 700 kVA",
            "c) 800 kVA",
            "d) 900 kVA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the remelting of steel, a high amount of power supply is needed by the direct arc furnace. The minimum transformer power supply needed by the furnace is 800 kVA. "
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "What is the capacity of a largest direct arc furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 110 tons",
            "b) 115 tons",
            "c) 125 tons",
            "d) 140 tons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The direct arc furnace is widely used in the steel foundries for the remelting unit. The largest direct arc furnace is found to have a capacity of 125 tons for remelting steel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "What is the maximum transformer power supply needed by the direct arc furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35,000 kVA",
            "b) 40,000 kVA",
            "c) 45,000 kVA",
            "d) 50,000 kVA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "What is typically the diameter of a direct arc furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Up to 5m",
            "b) Up to 6m",
            "c) Up to 7m",
            "d) Up to 8m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The direct arc furnace is widely used in the steel foundries for remelting steels of various compositions. In general, the diameter of a direct arc furnace is found to be only up to 6 meters. "
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "What would be the amount of current carried by the electrode for a direct arc furnace having capacity 50 tons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25 kilo amperes",
            "b) 25 mega amperes",
            "c) 25 micro amperes",
            "d) 25 nano amperes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a direct arc furnace having a capacity of around 50 tons, the electrode would carry a current of approximately 25,000 amperes, which is 25 kA. These electrodes can be moved upwards and downwards. "
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "How much is the thermal efficiency of a direct arc furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50%",
            "b) 60%",
            "c) 70%",
            "d) 80%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The roofs of the furnace bear with many damages during the operations. A few spare roofs should always be available since the roof does not have a very long life. "
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Which of the following material is not melted by an indirect electric arc furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Steel",
            "b) Copper",
            "c) Cast iron",
            "d) Zinc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An indirect electric arc furnace cannot be used for melting zinc, but for melting steel, cast iron or copper and its alloys, this method can be used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "What is the maximum capacity of a rocking furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 ton",
            "b) 1 ton",
            "c) 2 tons",
            "d) 3 tons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An indirect arc furnace or a rocking furnace has its capacity ranging from a few kilograms to up to 2 tons. It is generally used for smaller melts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors keeps the liquid metal level below the pouring sprout?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Angle of rocking furnace",
            "b) Velocity of rocking furnace",
            "c) Mounting distance",
            "d) Temperature of the metal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the operation of indirect electric arc furnace, the liquid metal level has to be kept below the pouring sprout level. To accomplish this, the angle of rocking adjusts itself in different manners and maintains the liquid level. "
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "How does the heat transfer take place in the rocking furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radiation-conduction",
            "b) Conduction-convection",
            "c) Convection-radiation",
            "d) Only radiation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a rocking furnace, the heat is first radiated from the hot refractory walls and the arc and conduction when the furnace starts rocking from the wall lining. "
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not valid for rocking furnace operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Causes overheating",
            "b) Uniform composition of melt",
            "c) Damage to the refractory lining",
            "d) Fast melting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In an indirect electric arc furnace, the rocking of furnace causes the melting to speed up, it also causes uniform composition of melt and does some damage to the refractory lining. This process does not cause overheating, instead it avoids it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Which metal is charged before the actual operation in a rocking furnace begins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gray iron",
            "b) Copper",
            "c) Pig iron",
            "d) Zinc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Inside the furnace, before beginning the actual process, the pig iron is charged. Above this charged pig iron, the scrap is then placed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "The electrodes used in the rocking furnace are typically made up of which material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminium",
            "b) Zinc",
            "c) Magnesium",
            "d) Graphite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In an indirect electric arc furnace, the electrodes are made up of graphite generally. When the scrap is placed, these electrodes are brought near for the current to jump. "
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "Where does the diameter of the electrode, in rocking furnace become low?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Near cathode",
            "b) Near anode",
            "c) In the middle",
            "d) Between cathode and the mid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The graphite electrode is designed in such a way that its diameter gets reduced at the middle of the electrode. This reduction in diameter causes a high amount of resistance in the electrode, hence generating large amount of heat. "
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "The oil of which metal is used in high frequency induction furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zinc",
            "b) Copper",
            "c) Aluminium",
            "d) Iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a high frequency induction furnace, the refractory is placed inside the water cooled copper oil and is packed into its position by ramming it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "A high frequency induction furnace can melt metal up to what mass?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 tons",
            "b) 11 tons",
            "c) 12 tons",
            "d) 13 tons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A high frequency induction furnace is used for the melting of comparatively small quantities. Metals up to the mass of 12 tons can be melted using this process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "What causes uniformity in the melt composition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electric stirring",
            "b) Electric shaking",
            "c) Magnetic stirring",
            "d) Magnetic shaking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For ensuring uniformity, a magnetic stirrer is employed, in a high frequency induction furnace. This magnetic stirrer distributes the composition of the melt excellently as needed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "Which currents are used for inducing heat in the high frequency induction furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alternating primary currents",
            "b) Direct primary currents",
            "c) Alternating secondary currents",
            "d) Direct secondary currents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A heavy amount of alternating secondary current, by electromagnetic induction, is induced in the metal charge. This causes the metal to get heated, because of the resistance offered by the metal charge. "
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "How much is the thermal efficiency of a coreless high frequency induction furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50%",
            "b) 60%",
            "c) 70%",
            "d) 80%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As compared to a core type furnace, a coreless high frequency induction furnace has a lower efficiency. The thermal efficiency of a coreless furnace can be only up to 60%."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "What is the minimum frequency accepted for the motor, used in current production of high frequency induction furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 430 cycles/second",
            "b) 500 cycles/second",
            "c) 550 cycles/second",
            "d) 600 cycles/second"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In high frequency induction furnace, motors which are equipped for the production of high frequency current can have a minimum frequency of 500 cycles every second. "
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "What is the minimum frequency accepted for the spark gap converter, used in current production of high frequency induction furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10,000 cycles/second",
            "b) 15,000 cycles/second",
            "c) 20,000 cycles/second",
            "d) 25,000 cycles/second"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The process of melting is done very quickly by conduction and radiation, and magnetic stirring makes uniform distribution of the melt composition, which reduces time. Hence time taken by the charge to melt is short. "
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "What is the maximum frequency accepted for the motor, used in current production of high frequency induction furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5000 cycles/second",
            "b) 10000 cycles/second",
            "c) 7500 cycles/second",
            "d) 12500 cycles/second"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Spark gap converters which are equipped for the production of high frequency current can have a minimum frequency of 20,000 cycles every second, in high frequency induction furnace. "
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "What is the maximum frequency accepted for the spark gap converter, used in current production of high frequency induction furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 70,000 cycles/second",
            "b) 75,000 cycles/second",
            "c) 80,000 cycles/second",
            "d) 85,000 cycles/second"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Motors which are equipped for the production of high frequency current can have a maximum frequency of 10000 cycles every second, in high frequency induction furnace. "
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "A low frequency induction furnace works on what frequency current?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 cycles/second",
            "b) 50 cycles/second",
            "c) 60 cycles/second",
            "d) 70 cycles/second"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A low frequency induction furnace works on an alternating current supply. This alternating current possess a frequency of 60 cycles every second. "
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be controlled by a core type furnace for any material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressure",
            "b) Volume",
            "c) Temperature",
            "d) Rate of production"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Any core type furnace can be used as a holding furnace for die casting as well as for permanent mold, as these furnaces are able to control the temperature of the metal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "What is the thermal efficiency of a low frequency induction furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60%",
            "b) 70%",
            "c) 80%",
            "d) 90%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Any core type induction surface has a high amount of thermal efficiency. A low frequency induction furnace has a thermal efficiency of 80%."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "What is the maximum capacity of a low frequency induction furnace in general?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 tons",
            "b) 5 tons",
            "c) 6 tons",
            "d) 7 tons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum capacity observed normally in a low frequency induction furnace is about 5 tons, which means, the furnace is able to operating on metals and alloys up to the mass of 5 tons. "
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "What is the maximum power which can be provided for a low frequency induction furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 350 kW",
            "b) 400 kW",
            "c) 450 kW",
            "d) 500 kW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The maximum power which can be provided to a low frequency induction furnace is about 500000 watts, which is 50 kW. The minimum power which can be provided to it is approximately 60W. "
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "What is the rate of melting of a low frequency induction furnace per kW rating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 – 3 kg/hr",
            "b) 2 – 3.5 kg/hr",
            "c) 3 – 4 kg/hr",
            "d) 3 – 4.5 kg/hr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rate of melting of a low frequency induction furnace is around 2 to 3.5 kg per hour per kilo watt rating of the furnace. "
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "What is the amount of loss suffered by an induction heating furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1%",
            "b) 2%",
            "c) 3%",
            "d) 4%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A primary coil is employed in the working of a low frequency induction furnace. The coil is wound on laminated steel core and the secondary coil has one turn which is a channel or a loop. "
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "Cast iron castings cannot be produced by melting which of the following materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pig iron",
            "b) Steel scrap",
            "c) Iron",
            "d) Copper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the melting of steel, there are losses suffered in the operation. In an induction heating furnace, the losses suffered are only about 1%."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the main advantage of using investment casting method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Better quality",
            "b) Low cost",
            "c) Complex shapes",
            "d) Reusable mould"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In investment casting method, wax is used as pattern material on which slurry is coated and then wax is taken out by melting it. This process of casting is widely used for producing complex shapes of castings. It has many other advantages like good dimensional accuracy and rapid production rate of the casting components."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the drawback of using the low-pressure die casting technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Material loss",
            "b) Time consuming",
            "c) Much labour work",
            "d) Uneconomical for small scale production"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sand casting is a process which is widely used for the production of simple casting products and it is very economical method of casting as compared to other methods of castings because the mould making process is very cheap process, so low cost is involved in the operations and it can be used for casting almost all the alloys."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the advantage of using the permanent mould casting method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mould can be used again and again",
            "b) Good thermal conductivity of mould",
            "c) Very complex shapes of casting can be produced",
            "d) Low cost process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The metal does not get wasted by the slush casting method. Even this method saves the molten metal by collecting it, which can be reused for the other casting process. This method makes the casting light in weight by saving the molten metal; hence this method is very economical for the production of castings."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the main advantage of using the centrifugal casting method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Defects less casting",
            "b) Maximum casting yield",
            "c) Low cost",
            "d) Fast production of castings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Low-pressure die casting technique is not economical for small-scale production because the machines used in the processes are very expensive, the parts like riser tube and the device used for compressing the gas makes this method very expensive. So this method is only economical when it is used for large scale productions."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the main disadvantage of using the hot chamber die casting process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High tooling cost",
            "b) Slow production rate",
            "c) Rough surface finish",
            "d) Not economical for large scale production"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In permanent mould casting method, a metallic mould is used which can be used again and again, and it has good thermal conductivity too. But this method is not appropriate for producing very complex shapes of castings. For complex shapes casting, the investment casting method is mainly preferred which can produce high extent of complexities in the casting components."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the drawback of using the sand casting process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Limited alloys",
            "b) Expensive mould",
            "c) Uneconomical for low quantities",
            "d) Labour intensive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the squeeze casting method, the main purpose is to produce castings of compact size with better strength. In this method, product quality is greatly improved by solidifying the casting under heavy pressure to prevent the dissolving of gases in the solution until the solidification of the casting is completed."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the main drawback of using the shell mould casting method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Limited size of casting parts",
            "b) High cost",
            "c) Rough surface finish",
            "d) Slow rate production"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In centrifugal casting technique, there is no need for the gates and runners to be used in the process, which can save a lot of molten metal. This makes the increase in casting yield which can reach to the maximum that means negligible metal loss. And no cores are required during the process which makes this method very economical for the large scale production of castings."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "Which of the following casting techniques is the best technique for casting tubes and hollow pipes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Die casting",
            "b) Slush casting",
            "c) Centrifugal casting",
            "d) Investment casting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In die casting technique, the casting process starts when the parts of the die are apart. It generally consists of two parts in which one part is called as stationary half or cover die that fixed to the die casting machine. Another part is called a moving part or ejector die that can slide for extracting out the casted product. "
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "Which of the following devices is used for generating the electron beam in electron beam melting process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Beam striker",
            "b) Beam laser",
            "c) Electron beam gun",
            "d) Electron runner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The electron beam technology is several times more efficient as compared to the laser technology. This technology results in less power consumption, less maintenance and low manufacturing costs. In this technology, electron beam melting process combines with vacuum, which can provide high power and excellent material properties.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the advantage of using the electron beam melting technology?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low cost",
            "b) Good surface finish",
            "c) Low maintenance",
            "d) Negligible impurities"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In this technology, first the part is designed by the 3D CAD software, and then the file is transferred to the processing software where the geometry is sliced into thin layers. The material is melted by electron beam to fit the geometry defined by the computer model. Then the metal parts are made by layers forming via electron beam melting process in a vacuum chamber."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of developer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dry powder",
            "b) Water soluble developer",
            "c) Oil soluble developer",
            "d) Water suspendible developer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Dye penetrant test is one of the methods of non-destructive testing of the components. The application of developer is one of the steps of inspection of dye penetrant test. Oil soluble developer is not a type of developer. "
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "For how long is a penetrant allowed to soak in cracks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 to 15 minutes",
            "b) 10 to 30 minutes",
            "c) 15 to 35 minutes",
            "d) 20 to 40 minutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "Penetrants of which colour are not used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Red",
            "b) Blue",
            "c) Green",
            "d) Yellow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The application of penetrant is one of the steps of inspection of dye penetrant test. It is an important feature that one must take care of, that the penetrant used, must not be of red colour, as defects are identified using red colour. "
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an excess penetrant remover?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solvent removable",
            "b) Water washable",
            "c) Lipophilic pre-emulsifiable",
            "d) Lipophilic post-emulsifiable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A penetrant remover material highly depends on the type of material by which the penetrant is made. Among the following, a lipophilic pre-emulsifiable is not a type of excess penetrant remover. "
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a method of pre-cleaning?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solvent",
            "b) Acid blasting",
            "c) Vapour degreasing",
            "d) Media blasting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The application of pre-cleaning is one of the steps of inspection of dye penetrant test. Solvent, alkaline, vapour degreasing and media blasting are a few types of pre-cleaning process, but not acid blasting. "
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of penetrant application?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dipping",
            "b) Spraying",
            "c) Brushing",
            "d) Pouring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The application of penetrant is one of the steps of inspection of the dye penetrant test. Among these, dipping, spraying or brushing are different ways by which penetrant can be applied, but not pouring. "
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "Which of the following defect is not detected by dye penetrant test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-metallic inclusions",
            "b) Leaks",
            "c) Cracks",
            "d) Forging defects"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dye penetrant test is one of the methods of non-destructive testing of the components. Leaks, cracks and forging defects are some defects which can be identified by using dye penetrant test. But, for detecting non-metallic inclusions, one will have to do a magnaflux test. "
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "What is the amount of time taken for blotting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 minutes",
            "b) 10 minutes",
            "c) 15 minutes",
            "d) 20 minutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The process of inspection is one of the steps of the important of dye penetrant test. The operation of inspection begins after the article is allowed to blot for around ten minutes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "Which of the following defects are not detected by magnetic particle inspection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface cracks",
            "b) Quenching cracks",
            "c) Thermal cracks",
            "d) Fatigue cracks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Quenching cracks, thermal cracks, grinding cracks or fatigue cracks are a few types of defects which can be detected by magnetic particle test, whereas surface cracks are defects which can be detected by simple visual inspection. "
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "When an AC current is used for magnaflux test, what is its frequency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35 cycles/sec",
            "b) 45 cycles/sec",
            "c) 55 cycles/sec",
            "d) 65 cycles/sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A magnaflux test is the one which is used for testing and detecting for any kind of thermal defect or any kind of quenching crack. For doing this, an alternating current can be used. The frequency of the alternating current is in the range of 50 to 60 cycles every second. "
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials can be tested using magnetic particle testing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brass",
            "b) Steel",
            "c) Bronze",
            "d) Solder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Among the following materials, only ferrous materials can be tested using a magnetic particle test, which is therefore steel. Brass and bronze are copper alloys and solder is an alloy of zinc, lead and tin. "
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Which current is helpful in detecting sub surface discontinuities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High frequency AC",
            "b) Low frequency AC",
            "c) Full wave DC",
            "d) Half wave DC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "Which current is helpful in detecting surface breaking indication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High frequency AC",
            "b) Low frequency AC",
            "c) Full wave DC",
            "d) Half wave DC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "Magnetic particles with fluorescent coating are seen under which light?",
        "Options": [
            "a) White light",
            "b) Infrared light",
            "c) Black light",
            "d) Ultraviolet light"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In magnetic particle testing, only ferrous materials can be tested using a magnetic particle test. The casting which is undergoing magnetic inspection, if it is coated with fluorescence, then it has to be viewed in an ultraviolet light only. "
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "What is the skin depth of copper at 60 Hz frequency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8 mm",
            "b) 8.5 mm",
            "c) 9 mm",
            "d) 9.5 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The distribution of an alternating electric current inside the conductor, and the flow of current through the skin of the material is called skin effect. The depth of the skin effect is skin depth. For copper, at frequency 60 Hz, the skin depth is 8.5mm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "What is the size range of dry particle powder?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 to 170 micrometers",
            "b) 15 to 185 micrometers",
            "c) 45 to 215 micrometers",
            "d) 65 to 250 micrometers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dry particle powder is basically applied in the form of a spray or a cloud. This powder is designed to be seen in white light. The particle size of dry particle powder is 5 to 170 micrometers. "
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Eddy current testing does not work below what thickness of materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 mm",
            "b) 0.2 mm",
            "c) 0.3 mm",
            "d) 0.4 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is one of the limitations of eddy current that defects having a thickness larger than required cannot be detected using eddy current method. Conventionally eddy current method cannot detect surface defects below 0.1 mm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Eddy currents are not used for the measure of which of the following properties?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrical conductivity",
            "b) Magnetic resistivity",
            "c) Hardness",
            "d) Grain size"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The inspection of structures done by eddy current method is based on the principle of electromagnetic induction. This method of detecting defects can be used for knowing the measure of electrical conductivity, grain size, hardness and magnetic permeability. "
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "Eddy current inspection method cannot be detect which of the following defect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Laps",
            "b) Seams",
            "c) Voids",
            "d) Surface crack"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "What is the heat generated in eddy current operations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) VI",
            "b) VIR",
            "c) I2RT",
            "d) I2R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For making perfect measurements and calculations, a few artificial defects were tried and a small hole was selected as the standard. The small drilled hole was selected because, it was not just easy to produce, but also, it was produced in precise sizes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "The signal display of eddy current system does not take place on which of the following media?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oscilloscope",
            "b) Oscillograph",
            "c) Electric tape",
            "d) Magnetic tape"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Eddy current method of inspection and heating techniques is used for metal heating. The heat generated by this method can be given by I2R, I is current and R is the resistance. "
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "For measuring glue line thickness between aluminium sheets, what should the thickness of the sheet be?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.2 mm",
            "b) 1.4 mm",
            "c) 1.6 mm",
            "d) 1.8 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Eddy current method is used as a non-destructive technique. Most of the times, a magnetic tape is used or a oscilloscope or an oscillograph, but not an electric tape. "
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "What is the conductivity of a 7075-T6 aluminium sheet with an average thickness of 1.6 mm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 IACS",
            "b) 31 IACS",
            "c) 32 IACS",
            "d) 33 IACS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is one of the limitations of eddy current testing that, below a certain thickness of the surface defect, the defect cannot be detected. This particular problem can be overcome by using multifrequency testing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "With an increase in the density of the material who does it affect the power loss in eddy current?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Does not change",
            "d) Not related"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For measuring the glue line thickness of aluminium sheets using eddy current method, initially the surface has to be vitally cleaned. The thickness of the aluminium sheet for calculating glue line thickness is 1.6mm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "What is typically the frequency used in ultrasonic inspection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 MHz to 15 MHz",
            "b) 0.5 MHz to 13 MHz",
            "c) 1 MHz to 17 MHz",
            "d) 1.8 MHz to 19 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ultrasonic testing is one of the most commonly used method for testing of materials. The general frequency of ultrasonic testing is in the range of 0.1 MHz to 15 MHz. "
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "What is the maximum frequency used in the ultrasonic inspection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35 MHz",
            "b) 40 MHz",
            "c) 45 MHz",
            "d) 50 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The maximum frequency that may be needed for an ultrasonic inspection is around 50 MHz. Such frequencies make it easy for the devices to detect the flaws. "
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "In which of the following materials, ultrasonic testing cannot be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plastics",
            "b) Ceramics",
            "c) Non-ferrous objects",
            "d) Ferrous object"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ultrasonic testing is a method for detecting flaws in the article. It can be used on various materials like plastics, ceramics and non-ferrous objects. "
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "On what voltage do the X-rays operate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 350 kV",
            "b) 375 kV",
            "c) 400 kV",
            "d) 475 kV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The X-ray are waves are having very short wavelength. The object which has to be tested is exposed to the X-rays, for doing this, high voltage supply is required. The X-rays ideally operate on 400 kV. "
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "X-rays are useful in detecting defects in casts up to what thickness?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60 mm",
            "b) 61 mm",
            "c) 62 mm",
            "d) 63 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The X-rays are waves of high amount of energy in them and are very useful in the detection of defects in the casts. They need a high amount of voltage supply for this and are able to detect defects up to a thickness of 62mm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "What is the lower range of wavelength of the X-rays?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.001 x 10-5 cm",
            "b) 0.001 x 10-6 cm",
            "c) 0.001 x 10-7 cm",
            "d) 0.001 x 10-8 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: X-rays are known to be waves with very low amount of wavelength. For the production of X-rays, one may usually need an X-ray tube. The shortest X-ray wavelength is calculated to be 0.001 x 10-8 cm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "What is the lower range of wavelength of the X-rays?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 x 10-7 cm",
            "b) 40 x 10-8 cm",
            "c) 40 x 10-9 cm",
            "d) 40 x 10-10 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The X-rays are considered to be rays having a short wavelength. These X-rays can be produced with the help of an X-ray tube or a Cobalt-60 isotope. The longest wavelength of an X-ray is 40 x 10-8 cm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a source of production for gamma rays?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cobalt-60",
            "b) Iridium-192",
            "c) Caesium-167",
            "d) Americium-241"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Among all the above given isotopes, a Cobalt – 60 isotope, Iridium-192 isotope and a Caesium-167 isotope are mainly used for producing gamma rays but not Americium-241 isotope, it is used for making alpha rays. "
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "What should the diameter of a Cobalt-60 source used for producing gamma rays?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 mm",
            "b) 3 mm",
            "c) 4 mm",
            "d) 5 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For the production of gamma rays, there are some radioactive particles employed. One of them is a Cobalt-60 isotope. The diameter of the source of this isotope is calculated to be around 3 mm in length. "
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "For what thickness of a material, do the X-rays give the best results?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 mm",
            "b) 55 mm",
            "c) 60 mm",
            "d) 65 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: X-rays are considered to be having a larger wavelength as compared to that of gamma rays. Owing to this fact, the penetration power of the X-rays is less. Hence, for a shorter thickness, it would give good detection. The best results are obtained in X-ray detection when the thickness of the material is below 50mm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be a wavelength of gamma ray?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 x 10-8 cm",
            "b) 3 x 10-8 cm",
            "c) 4 x 10-8 cm",
            "d) 5 x 10-8 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gamma rays are supposedly known to have a shorter wavelength as compared to that of X-rays. The wavelength of gamma rays ranges from 0.005 x 10-8 cm to 3 x 10-8 cm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "Which of the following components is mainly manufactured by performing metal forging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Piston",
            "b) Engine block",
            "c) Connecting rod",
            "d) Crankcase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Forming is basically a term that covers many manufacturing processes. In the metal forming process, the shape of the material or metal is changed by performing an operation like hammering, squeezing, bending, pulling etc. without changing its phase. The raw materials used in the forming process remained in a single solid phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Which of the following metal forming processes performs squeezing out of material through a hole?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forging",
            "b) Rolling",
            "c) Drawing",
            "d) Extrusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Connecting rod is mainly manufactured by forging operation which is specifically known as hot forging process, while parts like piston, crankcase and engine blocks are manufactured by a casting process. In the forging process, a hammer is used which strikes on the heated metallic part to get into the desired shape."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes is not the type of bulk forming process in the metal forming?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bending",
            "b) Rolling",
            "c) Forging",
            "d) Extrusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Metal forging is a forming operation which usually performs hammering process to shape the metal part. In the forging process, the metal part is heated sufficiently, and then it is hammered by using a hammer which can be performed by manual means or by automation, depending on the scale of production."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Which of the following manufacturing processes is mainly considered for producing the components of very high strength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Casting",
            "b) Forging",
            "c) Extrusion",
            "d) Rolling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Extrusion process is a type of metal forming process, in which the material is forced or squeezed out through a hole called die. This process is very similar to squeezing out the toothpaste from the tube. This process is mainly used for metals that are ductile in nature like copper, steel, aluminum and magnesium; this process is also used for polymers."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "Which of the following metal forming processes is best suitable for making the wires?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forging",
            "b) Extrusion",
            "c) Drawing",
            "d) Rolling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In general, the metal forming is a large set of manufacturing processes in which the metal is deformed plastically to get into the shape of the die geometry. The tools like dies and punches are mostly used in the processes for the deformation of the material. For the plastic deformation, Stresses beyond the yield strength of the material is required. "
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "Which of the following components are manufactured by the sheet metal forming process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Engine blocks",
            "b) Connecting rods",
            "c) Electric wires",
            "d) Car bodies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sheet metal forming is a process which uses ductile materials like aluminium or low carbon steel to form lightweight products with versatile features. Car bodies are mainly manufactured by sheet metal forming by performing operations like shearing, slitting, cutting, or sawing of thin metal plates. This method is also used for making parts like beverage cans, metal desks, appliances etc. "
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes is not the type of metal forming process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extrusion",
            "b) Injection moulding",
            "c) Forging",
            "d) Drawing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Extrusion, forging and drawing process are the main general types of metal forming process, while the injection moulding is other process which is basically a part of casting process which includes the formation of parts by injecting the melt into a cavity by the help of a plunger. This method is not the part of metal forming because the phase change of metal occurs during the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "Which of the following manufacturing processes operates under the influence of external forces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metal forming",
            "b) Powder metallurgy",
            "c) Casting",
            "d) Welding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: On the basis of temperature, metal forming mainly has two types which are cold forming and hot forming. Hot forming is defined as the mechanical working of metal at higher temperature above its re-crystallization temperature. And cold forming is a process which works at temperature below the re-crystallization temperature of metal."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Which of the following stresses is takes place during performing the wire drawing operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tensile stress",
            "b) Bending stress",
            "c) Indirect compressive stress",
            "d) Shear stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the metal forming process, the raw material is converted into a desired shape by the application of external force. The metal work piece is subjected to plastic deformation which results in changing of shape and size of the work piece or specimen under the influence of external forces or stresses. "
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "Which of the following can help in determining the behaviour of the material in metal forming?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size of material",
            "b) Shape of material",
            "c) Stress-strain curve",
            "d) Color of material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The behaviour of materials during metal forming can be determined by the stress-strain curve. The stress-strain curve for most of the materials is divided into an elastic region and a plastic region. In metal forming, the plastic region is the main consideration because the material is plastically deformed during the forming process."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of rolling mill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two-high rolling mill",
            "b) Cluster rolling mill",
            "c) Separation rolling mill",
            "d) Tandem rolling mill"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Among two-high rolling mill, cluster rolling mill, separation rolling mill and tandem rolling mill. Separation rolling mill is not a type of rolling mills. "
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "In two high rolling mill, what is the direction of rolling of the two rollers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clockwise-anticlockwise",
            "b) Clockwise-clockwise",
            "c) Anticlockwise-Anticlockwise",
            "d) Stationery-clockwise"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In two high rolling mill, the direction of both the rollers is opposite to one another. Hence, one clockwise while other anti-clockwise. "
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "In two high rolling mill, if the direction of the rollers is reversed, what is it called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two high backward mill",
            "b) Two high beneath mill",
            "c) Two high reversing mill",
            "d) Two high anti mill"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In two high rolling mill, if the direction of the roller is reversed, then that system is called as, two high reversing mill. "
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "In three high rolling mill, what is the direction of rolling of the three rollers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clockwise-clockwise- clockwise",
            "b) Clockwise-anticlockwise- anticlockwise",
            "c) Clockwise-anticlockwise- clockwise",
            "d) Anticlockwise-anticlockwise-anti clockwise"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In three high rolling mill, the direction of the rollers in the top and bottom are the same, and the direction of the roller in the middle is opposite to the two. "
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "How many rollers are used in four high rolling mill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 8",
            "d) 14"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In four high rolling mill, there are four rolls employed for roliing. The direction of two rollers is the same and the remaining two rollers roll in opposite directions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "Which of the following property does not improve in the hot rolling process, of a cast?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ductility",
            "b) Shock resistance",
            "c) Toughness",
            "d) Boiling point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The shape and the cross section shape of the billet, which is desired is not obtained in one single pass. One may have to use multiple pass to achieve desired cross section shape. "
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "Which of the following articles cannot be made from rolling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rails",
            "b) Helmets",
            "c) Bars",
            "d) Plates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When a rolled stack is made, there is an improvement seen in the physical properties of the material, it does not affect the boiling point of the material. "
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "Before beginning the process, the ingots are heated up to what temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000°C",
            "b) 1200°C",
            "c) 1400°C",
            "d) 1600°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rolling is very useful for making articles like bars, plates and rails, but it cannot be used for making helmets. For making helmets, different methods of casting are used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "During rolling process, the thickness of workpiece squeezed is called what?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shaft",
            "b) Bore",
            "c) Draft",
            "d) Core"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: During rolling process, the workpiece gets squeezed, causing the thickness of the workpiece to reduce. This reduced thickness is called a draft. "
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "With an increase in starting thickness, how would it affect the reduction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Won’t change",
            "d) Not related"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the starting thickness of the workpiece gets increased, the reduction of correspondingly gets decreased. "
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "How is the draft calculated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Difference between starting and final thickness",
            "b) Sum of starting and final thickness",
            "c) Product of starting and final thickness",
            "d) Ratio of starting and final thickness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Draft is calculated as, the difference between the starting thickness of the workpiece and the final thickness of the workpiece. "
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "Which of the following has the most magnitude?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slip velocity",
            "b) Surface velocity",
            "c) Entering velocity",
            "d) Exiting velocity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Exiting velocity, among the given four velocities, that is slip velocity, surface velocity, entering velocity and exiting velocity, the exiting velocity is considered to be having most magnitude. "
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Which of the following has least magnitude?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slip velocity",
            "b) Surface velocity",
            "c) Entering velocity",
            "d) Exiting velocity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "When a metal is entering, how are the width and the length of the workpiece related to each other?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct relation",
            "b) Inverse relation",
            "c) Exponential relation",
            "d) No relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the metal is entering, the width of the metal is inversely proportional to the length of the workpiece, that is, with an increase in the width of the metal, there would be a decrease in the length of the workpiece and vice versa. "
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "When a material is being rolled, the perpendicular force on the arc is called what?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thickness force",
            "b) Roll force",
            "c) Angle force",
            "d) Die force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Exiting velocity is has the most magnitude when compared to the other velocities, and is higher than the roll velocity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "How would the draft be affected, if the radius of the roller is decreased?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Won’t change",
            "d) Not related"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There is a force perpendicular to the arc which is in contact when the rolls are pressurizing the material. This force is called a roll force. "
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "How is the strength of the material, which is to be rolled, reduced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rolling at low temperatures",
            "b) Rolling at high temperatures",
            "c) Treating with ozone",
            "d) Treating with carbon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the material to be squeezed is rolled at high temperatures, the strength of the material is found to decrease. "
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "When the material is entering the roller, what is the tension at the entry zone called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Front tension",
            "b) Above tension",
            "c) Back tension",
            "d) Beneath tension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the material is entering the roller, the tension experienced at the entering zone is called as back tension. "
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "When the material is exiting the roller, what is the tension at the exit zone called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Front tension",
            "b) Above tension",
            "c) Back tension",
            "d) Beneath tension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "What increases when the take up reel rotates at a high speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Front tension",
            "b) Above tension",
            "c) Back tension",
            "d) Beneath tension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Among front tension, above tension, back tension and beneath tension, front tension is found to increase when the take up wheel rotates at a high speed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a thread rolling machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cylindrical die machine",
            "b) Reciprocating flat die machine",
            "c) Rotary planetary machines",
            "d) Quick return motion machine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Among the following, a quick return motion machine is not any type of thread rolling machine, while the remaining are thread rolling machines. "
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of a pass?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roll down pass",
            "b) Starter pass",
            "c) Leader pass",
            "d) Finishing pass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Among the following types of passes, starter pass is not any type of pass, while the remaining three are different types of passes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "How many dies are used in reciprocating flat die machines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thread rolling has it as one of its advantages, that there is no chip formation taking place, avoiding a lot of materials to be wasted. "
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "On what does the reciprocating die stroke depend on?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature",
            "b) Pressure",
            "c) Thread diameter",
            "d) Die radius"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a reciprocating flat die machine, there are only two dies which are used, one of them is stationery, while the other is reciprocating. "
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "What is the general production rate in thread rolling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000 pieces per minute",
            "b) 2000 pieces per minute",
            "c) 3000 pieces per minute",
            "d) 4000 pieces per minute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In a reciprocating flat die machine, the reciprocating die stroke depends upon the thread diameter, and there are 2 dies used in this apparatus, out of which, one is stationery. "
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Which of the following cannot be regarded as a defect in rolled parts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inhomogeneous deformation",
            "b) Surface defect",
            "c) External cracking defect",
            "d) Internal structure defect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Among the following defects in rolled parts, external cracking defect cannot be termed as a defect in rolled parts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "Which of the following cannot be regarded as an internal structure defect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Edge crack",
            "b) Zipper cracks",
            "c) Alligatoring",
            "d) Quevering"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Among the following internal structure defects, quevering is not any kind of a defect which can be regarded as an internal structure defect. "
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "Which of the following defect occurs because of the bending of rolls?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zipper cracks",
            "b) Folds",
            "c) Laminations",
            "d) Alligatoring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wavy edges and zipper cracks can occur as defects in the material, if the rolls are bended, but not, folds or laminations or alligatoring. Their causes of occurrence are different. "
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "Which defect takes place if the reduction per mass is very low?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zipper cracks",
            "b) Folds",
            "c) Laminations",
            "d) Alligatoring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Folds are found to occur during the plate rolling if the reduction per mass is very low. And zipper cracks occur when the given rolls get bended. "
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "Incomplete welding may cause which of the following defect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Folds",
            "b) Laminations",
            "c) Wavy edges",
            "d) Zipper cracks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Because of incomplete welding in the blow holes and the pipes, small laminations occur, causing the strength of the material to reduce. "
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Which defect is rupturing of sheet and following the roller path?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Folds",
            "b) Laminations",
            "c) Alligatoring",
            "d) Wavy edges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the material is compressed against the rolls, the sheet may get ruptured, without laterally, the width getting converted to length. Such a defect is called as alligatoring. "
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "In which of the following defects is a crown formed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wavy edges",
            "b) Alligatoring",
            "c) Folds",
            "d) Laminations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In hot working processes, the temperature at which the work takes place is not uniform. There is change of temperature that takes place in between the process when it is going on. "
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "What is the open hearth called in which the metal is heated to its plastic state?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roger’s forging",
            "b) Black’s forging",
            "c) Smith’s forging",
            "d) Gold’s forging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The open hearth in which the metal is brought to its plastic state by increasing its temperature is called as Smith’s forging. "
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "Which of the following process is done above the recrystallization temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hot forging",
            "b) Cold forging",
            "c) Impact forging",
            "d) Gradual pressure forging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Among hot forging, cold forging, impact forging and gradual pressure forging, hot forging is done above the recrystallization temperature, but below the melting point. "
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is used for manufacturing screws?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hot forging",
            "b) Cold forging",
            "c) Impact forging",
            "d) Gradual pressure forging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For the manufacturing of products like screws, pins or nails, the process of hot forging or impact forging is not recommended. But, for this, cold forging is highly used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is used for manufacturing shafts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open die forging",
            "b) Closed die forging",
            "c) Impact forging",
            "d) Flashless forging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: While the manufacture of products like shafts, discs or rings, the method of closed die forging or impact forging or flashless forging is not advised, but open die forging is used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "In which of the following process, does the die have a concave surface?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fullering",
            "b) Edging",
            "c) Cogging",
            "d) Cavitising"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Among the following processes, that are fullering, edging, cogging and cavitising, edging is a process in which, the die has a concave shape. "
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "In which of the following process, does the die have a convex surface?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fullering",
            "b) Edging",
            "c) Cogging",
            "d) Cavitising"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Strain hardening is caused by cold forging, whereas hot forging results in a reduction of the strength of the material. "
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "Which of the following operation is called incremental forging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fullering",
            "b) Edging",
            "c) Cogging",
            "d) Cavitising"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "Which of the following process is used for making slabs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fullering",
            "b) Edging",
            "c) Cogging",
            "d) Cavitising"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Among the following process, cogging is the operation in which the surface is contoured a little. This process is also called as incremental forging. "
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "In which of the following processes most noise is produced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Press forging",
            "b) Drop forging",
            "c) Open die forging",
            "d) Closed die forging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Among the following processes, that is press forging, drop forging, open die forging and closed die forging, drop forging is a process where more amount of noise occurs. "
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "In which of the following processes most vibration is produced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Press forging",
            "b) Drop forging",
            "c) Open die forging",
            "d) Closed die forging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "Which of the following hammers is also called a gravity hammer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Board hammer",
            "b) Air-lift hammer",
            "c) Power drop hammer",
            "d) Nail hammer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Among the following type of drop hammers, that is, board hammer, air-lift hammer, power drop hammer and nail hammer, board hammer is also called a gravity hammer. "
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "Which of the following hammers is also called a steam hammer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Board hammer",
            "b) Air-lift hammer",
            "c) Power drop hammer",
            "d) Nail hammer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "In which of the following processes, life of dies is less?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hot forging",
            "b) Cold forging",
            "c) Drop forging",
            "d) Open die forging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It has been observed that press forging is a process which works more smoothly and is lot more accurate than drop forging. "
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "How much do the presses in press forging weigh?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200-300 tonnes",
            "b) 300-400 tonnes",
            "c) 400-500 tonnes",
            "d) 500-600 tonnes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In drop forging, the anvil is a lot heavier than the hammer. To absorb the blow caused by the hammer, the anvil is made 20 times heavier than the hammer. "
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is used for making wheel discs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drop forging",
            "b) Press forging",
            "c) Open die forging",
            "d) Closed die forging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In drop forging method, the forging is produced when there is a drop of the hammer on the metal. This causes the life of the hammer and the dies to be less. "
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is used for making crankshafts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drop forging",
            "b) Press forging",
            "c) Open die forging",
            "d) Closed die forging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The presses used for such forging processes are manufactured for very heavy use. The presses which are generally used in press forging are of the capacity of 500 to 600 tonnes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "Extrusion process is not suitable for which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Steel alloys",
            "b) Non-ferrous alloys",
            "c) Stainless steel",
            "d) Iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Extrusion process is not suitable for any of the iron alloys, neither is it suitable for iron metal. For extruding stainless steel or other non-ferrous alloys or steel alloys, extrusion process can be used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not made using extrusion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Window frames",
            "b) Doors",
            "c) Helmets",
            "d) Rods"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Among the following, helmets are not manufactured using extrusion, whereas all other products can be manufactured using extrusion. "
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "What is the shape of the billet used in extrusion process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cubical",
            "b) Spherical",
            "c) Cylindrical",
            "d) Pyramidal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The shape of the billet in an extrusion process is designed to be cylindrical only. A cubical or spherical or a pyramidal billet cannot be designed for a good output. "
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "Which of the following is also called as forward hot extrusion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct extrusion",
            "b) Indirect extrusion",
            "c) Impact extrusion",
            "d) Hydrostatic extrusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Direct extrusion is also called as forward hot extrusion. This method is most widely used and maximum production is done by this method in extrusion. "
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "Backward extrusion is another name for which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct extrusion",
            "b) Indirect extrusion",
            "c) Impact extrusion",
            "d) Hydrostatic extrusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Direct extrusion is also called as backward extrusion. In this method, the metal is extruded back into the plunger. "
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "In which of the following operations is a dummy block used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indirect extrusion",
            "b) Direct extrusion",
            "c) Impact extrusion",
            "d) Hydrostatic extrusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In direct extrusion or forward extrusion, a dummy block is used during the functioning of the extrusion process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "Up to what size can wires can be drawn by wire drawing process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01mm",
            "b) 0.02mm",
            "c) 0.03mm",
            "d) 0.04mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Indirect extrusion or backward extrusion does not require a large amount of force for operation, as the billet is stationery. "
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "Which of the following metal is used in the wire drawing process in die making?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Copper",
            "b) Iron",
            "c) Tungsten",
            "d) Magnesium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It may be counted among one of the limitations of drawing process, that very thin wires can only be drawn from it. In wire drawing process, wires can be drawn up to the size of 0.03mm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "Which of the following parts is used for holding the metal sheet during blanking operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spherical steel ball",
            "b) Roller",
            "c) Pressure pad",
            "d) Magnet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Blanking is a kind of shearing operation which is generally carried out along a closed contour. In this operation, the required part is the material inside the sheared contour which is called as blank. For example, circular blanks are taken out from the metal sheet for subsequent deep drawing of cups."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "Which of the following represents the approximate percentage of metal loss during the blanking operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2%",
            "b) 5%",
            "c) 10%",
            "d) 30%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Punching is basically a kind of shearing operation in which the required part is the sheet left out after making a punch hole in the metal sheet. This method is also known as contour shearing. Die punch clearance is generally very critical for blanking as well as for punching operation, as it maintains the kind of finish obtained on the final part."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Which of the following dies is not the type of cutting dies in the metal cutting operations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Squeezing dies",
            "b) Blanking dies",
            "c) Piercing dies",
            "d) Notching dies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the blanking or punching operation, the punch diameter should be smaller than the die hole. The clearance between the die and the punch basically depends on the type of process used. For example, for blanking operation, the clearance is provided on the punch for obtaining the blank from metal sheet."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods of manufacturing is used for the production of appliances like the fridge and vacuum cleaner?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forging",
            "b) Deep drawing",
            "c) Sheet metal forming and cutting",
            "d) Rolling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The raw material for the sheet metal forming is basically the output of the rolling process. IN the sheet metal forming process, flat rectangular solid sheets of standard sized are used and then the operations like piercing or blanking is performed on the metal sheets to obtain the desired output."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "What should be the appropriate thickness of the metal sheet when it is used as a raw material for the sheet metal operations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 cm to 5 cm",
            "b) 5 cm to 10 cm",
            "c) 7.5 mm to 15 mm",
            "d) 0.4 mm to 6 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sheet metal forming and cutting processes are widely used for the manufacturing of home appliances like fridge, vacuum cleaner radio, toys, dryers etc. In the sheet metal forming processes, bending operation is takes place which form the metal and sheet cutting is used for shearing out the metal part from the large metal sheet."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "Which of the following types of force is predominant in the sheet metal forming processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shearing force",
            "b) Compressive force",
            "c) Tensile force",
            "d) Indirect compressive force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cutting dies are mainly used for cutting the metal. They use shearing action for cutting the metal sheet. Various cutting dies are used such as blanking dies, piercing dies, perforating dies, notching dies, shaving dies and nibbling dies. And it is not possible to use cutting dies for the metal drawing operations."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials is used for the manufacturing of dies and punches in the sheet metal forming?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grey cast iron",
            "b) Copper",
            "c) Aluminium",
            "d) Carbide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The sheet metal forming and cutting operations are mainly performed on relatively thin sheets of metal. The thickness of metal sheet should be 0.4 mm to 6 mm to operate efficiently. If the thickness is more than 6 mm, then it is normally called as metal plate. The operations are generally performed as cold working. "
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes is mainly used for making the connecting rods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Casting",
            "b) Deep drawing",
            "c) Rolling",
            "d) Forging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Forging is a metal forming operation in which heated metal is beaten by a hammer to give it the desired shape. It is basically a deformation process in which the material is compressed between dies by using impact load to deform it. Forging can also be used for making complex shapes of metal parts."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods of forming is not the part of electromagnetic forming?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compression",
            "b) Expansion",
            "c) Shearing",
            "d) Counter forming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In electromagnetic forming, many components like capacitor bank, forming coil, field shaper, conductive material etc. are used to create intense magnetic fields. This magnetic is generally produced by the discharge of capacitors into a coil, which lasts only for a few microseconds. Then further processing is done to perform the metal forming.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the main advantage of using the electromagnetic forming process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High speed",
            "b) Low maintenance",
            "c) Applicable to all materials",
            "d) No spring-back"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the electromagnetic forming process, eddy currents are induced in a conductive material that is placed near to the coil. Then it interacts with a magnetic field to cause mutual repulsion between the metal and the forming coil. This force of repulsion is mainly responsible for inducing stresses in the metal beyond its yield strength which results in plastic deformation of metal."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "What is the melting point of pure iron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1500°C",
            "b) 1535°C",
            "c) 1570°C",
            "d) 1605°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Iron exists in many allotropic forms, and every such allotropic form has a different melting, boiling and solidifying point. But, for pure iron, the melting point is 1535°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "Which iron is formed when the melt is frozen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alpha",
            "b) Beta",
            "c) Gamma",
            "d) Delta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Alpha irons, beta irons or gamma irons cannot be formed when the metal is in the frozen form. When the molten metal is frozen, delta iron is formed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "What is the kind of lattice in a delta iron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Face centered cubic",
            "b) Body centered cubic",
            "c) Hexagonal closely packed",
            "d) Tetragonal closely packed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The delta form of solid state of iron, which is formed on cooling the melt, has a body centered cubic lattice structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "What is the kind of lattice in a gamma iron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Face centered cubic",
            "b) Body centered cubic",
            "c) Hexagonal closely packed",
            "d) Tetragonal closely packed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The gamma form of solid state of iron, which is formed on cooling the melt, has a face centered cubic lattice structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "In transformation in steel, hypo eutectoid steel are heated up to what temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 677°C",
            "b) 700°C",
            "c) 723°C",
            "d) 746°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In transformation in steel, the hypo eutectoid steels are heated up to a very high amount of temperature. The temperature to which they are taken is 723°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "What is the Brinell hardness of pearlite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 150",
            "b) 180",
            "c) 210",
            "d) 240"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pearlite is not the hardest form. The Brinell hardness of pearlite is only 180. There is a harder material than pearlite, called as martensite, which has Brinell hardness ranging from 650-700. "
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "How much is the Brinell hardness of martensite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 600-650",
            "b) 650-700",
            "c) 750-800",
            "d) 800-850"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is one of the properties of alpha irons that alpha irons are highly magnetic and they are found to exist only at room temperature. The alpha iron is the fourth retardation of iron. "
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "What is the value of ‘a’ in a delta iron lattice?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.00 Å",
            "b) 2.93 Å",
            "c) 4.00 Å",
            "d) 4.93 Å"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Martensite is a ferro-magnetic substance in nature, and it is known to have Brinell hardness ranging from 650-700. "
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "HPF steel is normalized at what temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 800°C",
            "b) 900°C",
            "c) 1000°C",
            "d) 1100°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The HPF steel has to be taken to high magnitudes of temperatures. The HPF steel or the hot press forming steel gets normalized at 900°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "What is the Vicker’s hardness of steel before the HPF process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 150 Hv",
            "b) 160 Hv",
            "c) 170 Hv",
            "d) 180 Hv"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The HPF process in steels is considered to be a very important process, it involves heating the steel to high temperatures. The Vickers hardness of steel before HPF process is 170 Hv. "
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "What is the Vickers hardness of steel after the HPF process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 362 Hv",
            "b) 462 Hv",
            "c) 562 Hv",
            "d) 662 Hv"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The HPF process is a very essential process. The Vickers hardness of the material is found to change after this process is done. The Vickers hardness of steel after HPF process is 462 Hv. "
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "What is the amount of carbon used in HPF steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less than 0.37%",
            "b) Less than 0.27%",
            "c) Less than 0.47%",
            "d) Less than 0.57%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The carbon content which is used in HPF steel is very less in percentage composition. The amount of carbon used in terms of percentage weight is less than 0.27%."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "What is the amount of silicon used in HPF steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less than 0.30%",
            "b) Less than 0.20%",
            "c) Less than 0.40%",
            "d) Less than 0.50%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The silicon content which is used in HPF steel is very less in percentage composition. The amount of silicon used in terms of percentage weight is less than 0.50%."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "What is the amount of boron used in HPF steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less than 0.003%",
            "b) Less than 0.007%",
            "c) Less than 0.009%",
            "d) Less than 0.057%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The boron content which is used in HPF steel is extremely less in percentage composition. The amount of boron used in terms of percentage weight is less than 0.003%."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "What is the amount of tungsten used in HPF steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less than 0.03%",
            "b) Less than 0.02%",
            "c) Less than 0.04%",
            "d) Less than 0.05%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The tungsten content which is used in HPF steel is very less in terms of percentage composition. The amount of tungsten used in terms of percentage weight is less than 0.05%."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "What is the amount of nitrogen used in HPF steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less than 0.03%",
            "b) Less than 0.02%",
            "c) Less than 0.04%",
            "d) Less than 0.05%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The nitrogen content which is used in HPF steel is very less in percentage composition.  The amount of nitrogen used in terms of percentage weight is less than 0.02%."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes is called as quenching?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slow cooling",
            "b) Slow heating",
            "c) Rapid cooling",
            "d) Rapid heating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Among the following, that is, slow cooling, slow heating, rapid cooling and rapid heating, quenching is the name given to the process of rapid cooling. "
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "On martensite formation, what is the percentage increase in the volume of the steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3%",
            "b) 13%",
            "c) 23%",
            "d) 33%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It has been observed that whenever there is a formation of martensite, there is some amount of increase in the volume accompanied by it. This increase in the volume is about 3%."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "How much is the Brinell hardness of sorbite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 250",
            "b) 350",
            "c) 450",
            "d) 550"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cementite in sorbite is known to be very finely divided. The material sorbite is not one of the hardest materials known in casting. The Brinell hardness of sorbite is 350. "
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "How much is the Brinell hardness of troostite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 250",
            "b) 350",
            "c) 450",
            "d) 550"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The cementite in the troostite is very finely divided. The material troostite is not one of the hardest materials known in casting.  The Brinell hardness of sorbite is 450. "
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "What is the chemical formula of cementite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fe3O4",
            "b) Fe2O3",
            "c) Fe3C",
            "d) FeSO4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "What is the crystal structure of cementite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Orthogonal",
            "b) Pyramidal",
            "c) Trapeziodal",
            "d) Orthorhombic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The crystal structure of the compound cementite or iron carbide is not orthogonal or pyramidal or trapezoidal, but it is orthorhombic. "
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "What is the curie temperature of cementite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 480K",
            "b) 500K",
            "c) 520K",
            "d) 540K"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The compound cementite is also called as Iron Carbide. The chemical formula of the compound cementite is Fe3C. The curie temperature of the compound cementite is approximately about 480K. "
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "What is the percentage weight of iron in cementite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 93.3%",
            "b) 94.3%",
            "c) 95.3%",
            "d) 96.3%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the compound iron carbide or cementite, the percentage weight of iron is 93.3% and the rest of the space in the lattice is occupied by carbon. By weight, carbon is present in about 6.67% in the mixture. "
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "What is the percentage weight of carbon in cementite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.53%",
            "b) 6.67%",
            "c) 7.23%",
            "d) 8.39%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an objective of annealing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Softening of steel",
            "b) Hardening of steel",
            "c) Increase ductility",
            "d) Relieve internal stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Among the many purposes of treating the steel through annealing is softening of steel, hardening of steel and relieving the internal stresses, but annealing is not used for hardening of the steel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "In full annealing, the steel is heated at what temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Above critical temperature",
            "b) Above vaporization temperature",
            "c) Above liquefying temperature",
            "d) Above solidification temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the process of full annealing, the steel has to be heated slightly above the critical temperature. At this point, the steel has to be held for a considerable amount of time. "
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "In annealing process, for the formation of hypereutectoid steel, the steel has to be heated above what point?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ac1",
            "b) Ac2",
            "c) Ac3",
            "d) Ac4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the formation of hypereutectoid steel, in annealing process, the steel has to be heated above the Ac1 point, which is the lower critical line in the temperature versus carbon content graph. "
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "In annealing process, for the formation of hypoeutectoid steel, the steel has to be heated above what point?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ac1",
            "b) Ac2",
            "c) Ac3",
            "d) Ac4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "For how long is the heated steel held in full annealing process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 minute",
            "b) 3 minutes",
            "c) 6 minutes",
            "d) 9 minutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The heated steel is held at the critical temperature for about 3 to 4 minutes. By doing this, the steel gets enough time to make the internal changes desired. "
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "In full annealing, the metal cannot be buried in which of the following materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sand",
            "b) Lime",
            "c) Ashes",
            "d) Manganese powder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the process, full annealing, if the metal is removed at high temperatures, they need to be buried. For this, the material cannot be manganese powder. "
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "Which of the following is also called as diffusion annealing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isothermal annealing",
            "b) Process annealing",
            "c) Homogenizing",
            "d) Spheroidise annealing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Annealing is considered to be a very slow process, as the part where the steel is cooled, takes up a lot of time for the process to get completed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "At what temperature is homogenizing carried out?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1150°C",
            "b) 1370°C",
            "c) 1420°C",
            "d) 1320°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Homogenising has another name as diffusion annealing. This method is applied to both the ingots, carbon as well as alloy steel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "Which of the following forming processes is suitable for making utensils and cup shaped objects?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forging",
            "b) Rolling",
            "c) Deep drawing",
            "d) Wire drawing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Deep drawing process is also known as cup drawing, which is a part of sheet metal forming process. It is widely used for making products like utensils, cup shaped objects, pressure vessels, gas cylinders, cans etc. In this method, a blank is placed on a die cavity and then held in a position using a holding plate and pressed against the die cavity by using a punch."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods of heat treatment is best suitable for treating the output of cold rolling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quenching",
            "b) Case hardening",
            "c) Annealing",
            "d) Cyanide hardening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In metal forming, cold working or rolling process is also known as work hardening process, which basically defined as the process of strengthening a material by plastic or permanent deformation. Plastic deformation occurs when a material is altered after its elastic region, this process makes the material hard and strong."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes of metal forming is best suited for making products like aircraft wings and window frames?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forging",
            "b) Rolling",
            "c) Drawing",
            "d) Stretch forming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Stretch forming is a type of sheet metal forming process in which the metallic sheet is intentionally stretched and bent simultaneously to produce different shapes of the stretched sheet metal. The metal sheet is generally held by jaws at the ends. And then the sheet is stretched by the help of punch. "
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "Which of the following types of stresses is applied during the process of rod or tube drawing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shear",
            "b) Direct compressive",
            "c) Tensile",
            "d) In-direct compressive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rod or tube drawing is a deformation process in which the metallic material in the form of cylindrical bar is pulled by the help of a converging die. In general, the tensile stress is applied during the process. The strain hardening occurs which makes the material very hard and strong by reducing its ductility."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes of metal forming is widely used for making the raw material for the manufacturing of bolts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rolling",
            "b) Forging",
            "c) Wire drawing",
            "d) Rod drawing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In rod drawing process, a bar or rod is drawn in order to reduce its diameter. The drawing operation results in the reduction in cross-sectional area of the material by increasing its length. This process is basically a kind of cold working process which takes place below the re-crystallization temperature of the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "Low carbon steels can be started to forge at what temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1140°C",
            "b) 1270°C",
            "c) 1350°C",
            "d) 1420°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Low carbon soft steels are generally used for making seamless and welded steel pipes, which can be used at very low temperatures. They can be forged at a temperature range of 1250°C to 1300°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "Low carbon steels get forged at what temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 670°C",
            "b) 730°C",
            "c) 820°C",
            "d) 950°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "At what temperature does the high carbon steel get forged?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 950°C",
            "b) 1510°C",
            "c) 1150°C",
            "d) 1290°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The high carbon steel is provided heat treatment, after this, the steel is allowed to quench and then tempered. They can be forged at a temperature of 1100°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "At what temperature does alloy steel get forged?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 850°C",
            "b) 970°C",
            "c) 1050°C",
            "d) 1200°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the improvisation of mechanical and physical properties of the materials, a variety of materials are added and to make it alloying steel. The temperature at which alloy steel can be forged is in the range of 825°C to 875°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "At what temperature does wrought irons get forged?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Below 1000°C",
            "b) Below 1100°C",
            "c) Below 1200°C",
            "d) Below 1300°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Wrought irons are identified as alloys of iron which contain very low amount of carbon in them. Wrought irons can be forged at a temperature below 1300°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "What is the forging temperature of brass?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 450°C",
            "b) 500°C",
            "c) 550°C",
            "d) 600°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Brass is an alloy of mainly two metals being, copper and zinc. These two metals can substitute each other’s place in the structure of the alloy. The temperature at which brass gets forged is about 600°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "What is the forging temperature of bronze?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 850°C",
            "b) 900°C",
            "c) 950°C",
            "d) 1000°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bronze is an alloy that essentially contains copper in it and generally is found to contain about 12% of tin. It may also have some other additives in it like, manganese, zinc or nickel. The temperature at which bronze gets forged is about 950°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "What is the forging temperature of magnesium alloys?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 450°C",
            "b) 500°C",
            "c) 550°C",
            "d) 600°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Metals such as zinc, copper, zirconium, silicon or aluminium are mixed with magnesium to form a magnesium alloy. In terms of structure, magnesium is considered to be the lightest metal. The temperature at which magnesium alloys get forged is 500°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "Which of the following operations involves reduction in length?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Upsetting",
            "b) Drawing down",
            "c) Setting down",
            "d) Punching"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are a few operations, which are needed for a change of shape of the raw material to its finished form. This can be achieved using smith forging operation. Upsetting is one such operation that involves reduction in length for an increase the thickness. "
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "Swaging is another name for which smith forging operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bending",
            "b) Punching",
            "c) Drawing down",
            "d) Cutting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Swaging is another name for the operation drawing down. In drawing down operation, the length of the material is found to increase at an expense of the width or thickness of it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "Which of the following operations involves the reduction in length?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Upsetting",
            "b) Drawing down",
            "c) Setting down",
            "d) Punching"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are a few operations, which are needed for a change of shape of the raw material to its finished form. This can be achieved using smith forging operation. Drawing down is one such operation that involves increase in length at the cost of its thickness. "
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "Which of the following material is not used as a flux in forge welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 parts of borax with one part of sal-ammoniac",
            "b) Quartz sand",
            "c) Calcined borax",
            "d) 3 parts of borax with one part of sal-ammoniac"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The metal which has to be welded, has to be first covered with flux. By covering it with flux, it cuts the metal from the air around and prevents from oxidation. The fluxes used for this purpose are quartz sand, calcined borax and 3 parts of borax with one part of sal-ammoniac. "
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "In which form of weld, are the ends joined?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lap weld",
            "b) Butt weld",
            "c) Jump weld",
            "d) Split weld"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In lap weld, the ends of the two metals which are to be joined are prepared for welding. In butt welding, the materials are butted are together. In split weld, the metals are kept like a fork in a ‘V’ shape. "
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "Which form of weld is also called as ‘T’ weld?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lap weld",
            "b) Butt weld",
            "c) Jump weld",
            "d) Split weld"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In butt welding, the materials are butted are together. In jump welding, the two pieces are kept at an angle of 90o, in the form of an inverted ‘T’. "
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "In cutting smith forging operation, up to what temperature is the steel heated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 700°C – 800°C",
            "b) 850°C – 950°C",
            "c) 900°C – 1000°C",
            "d) 1000°C – 1100°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cutting is a form of smith forging operation, it is a form of chiseling. For chiseling, a long piece of metal is cut into equal lengths. These equal lengths need to be heated till they are cherry red hot, which makes it a temperature of 850°C to 950°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "Which form of weld is also called as ‘V’ weld?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lap weld",
            "b) Butt weld",
            "c) Jump weld",
            "d) Split weld"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In butt welding, the materials are butted are together. In split weld, the metals are kept like a fork in a ‘V’ shape. "
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "In compressed impression die forging, what is typically the shape of the solid blanks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cylindrical",
            "b) Conical",
            "c) Spherical",
            "d) Pyramidal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In compressed impression die forging, it is generally observed that the shape of solid blanks is either cylindrical or prismatic only. The shape of the solid blanks is similar even in case of stamping industry. "
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an operation of impression die forging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Broaching",
            "b) Quenching",
            "c) Bending",
            "d) Spreading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are many basic and primary operations in impression die forging, a few of them are, broaching, bending, spreading, sizing and swaging. But, quenching is not any of the operations of impression die forging. "
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not produced using impression die forging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Levers",
            "b) Handles",
            "c) Gears",
            "d) Turbine blades"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Impression die forging finds itself into variety of applications. They are used in making a few automobile parts also. Among the following, levers, gears and turbine blades can be produced using impression die forging, but not handles. "
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "Which of the following are not operated in impression die forging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hammers",
            "b) Presses",
            "c) Tongs",
            "d) Special purpose machines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In impression die forging, there are various such articles which can be forged, but after that need a little working on it. To accomplish that, hammers, presses and some other special purpose machining tools are employed. A tong is not one of them. "
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "In forging dies, what is the maximum degree to which the drafts are made?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7o",
            "b) 10o",
            "c) 13o",
            "d) 18o"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In impression die forging, there has to be some amount of allowance given to the process, like machining allowance and draft allowance. The drafts are made with a maximum degree deviation of 10o. "
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "In forging dies, what is the minimum degree to which the drafts are made?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1o",
            "b) 2o",
            "c) 3o",
            "d) 4o"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are some types of allowances which have to be given to the system before the operations begin, like, shrinkage allowance, machining allowance and draft allowance. The minimum angle which can be given to the drafts is only 3o. "
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "What is the minimum temperature given before hot forging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100°C",
            "b) 150°C",
            "c) 200°C",
            "d) 250°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hot forging is a method of forging articles at an extremely high temperature. But, before putting the article into the hot forging processes, it has to be heated to certain temperatures. The minimum temperature that has to be given to the article should be 200°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "What is the maximum temperature that can should be given before hot forging process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 150°C",
            "b) 200°C",
            "c) 250°C",
            "d) 300°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In impression die forging, when any article has to be hot forged, it has to first be heated to bring at a certain temperature. The maximum temperature that can be provided for hot forging is 300°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not included in weldability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ability of mechanical soundness",
            "b) Serviceability of joint",
            "c) Strain relieving brittleness",
            "d) Metallurgical compatibility of metal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the making of good fabricated composition of a structure, metal with good weldability gets readily welded. Weldability includes the ability of the metal or the alloy to be having soundness in its mechanical properties, metallurgical compatibility of metal and serviceability of joint. "
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "Which effect is not seen in alloys on weldability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control of ductile-malleable transformation temperature",
            "b) Provision for oxidation to molten metal",
            "c) Reduction in segregation",
            "d) Grain refinement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: On weldability, there are some effects seen in the alloying elements. Some of them are Control of ductile-malleable transformation temperature, Reduction in segregation, Grain refinement and provision for deoxidation to the molten metal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "On which of the following factor, does weldability not depend?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boiling point",
            "b) Melting point",
            "c) Thermal expansion",
            "d) Thermal conductivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Weldability is dependent on five factors of the metal or alloying element. The factors being, melting point, thermal expansion, thermal conductivity, surface condition and change in the microstructure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a way of correcting the metal which does not have good weldability properties?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Procedure of welding",
            "b) Provision of fluxing material",
            "c) Provision of filler material",
            "d) Procedure of adding filler materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When a particular metal or an alloy does not have desirable welding characteristics, then it can be corrected by proper fluxing material, correct filler material and a perfect welding procedure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "What does HAZ stand for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Helium Aerated Zone",
            "b) Heated Area Zone",
            "c) Heat Affected Zone",
            "d) Heat Allowed Zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: HAZ stands for Heat Affected Zone. This zone is generally the base of the metal or a thermoplastic material. This zone is not melted but the properties are altered by the welding process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "With an increase in the heat input of arc welding method, how does it affect the welding speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) No relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In arc welding processes, for calculating the efficiency, we use the formula for heat input. According to the formula, heat input is inversely related to the speed of welding, that is, with an increase in heat input, the welding speed decreases. "
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "With an increase in the heat input of arc welding method, how does it affect the voltage applied?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) No relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "With an increase in the heat input of arc welding method, how does it affect the required current?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) No relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of arc welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plasma",
            "b) Electro-slag",
            "c) Submerged",
            "d) Air-acetylene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Among the following, plasma arc, electro-slag and submerged arc are few of the types of arc welding. Air-acetylene is one of the forms of gas welding processes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of resistance welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seam",
            "b) Projection",
            "c) Electro-slag",
            "d) Spot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Among the following, seam, projection and spot are few of the types of resistance welding. Electro-slag is one of the forms of gas welding processes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials are not suited for cold welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brass",
            "b) Steel",
            "c) Silver",
            "d) Gold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cold welding process is not very suitable for alloys like steel, the reason being, cold welding cannot take place excellently in ferrous materials. Steel contains high amount of iron, hence it cannot be cold welded. "
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "What is the cross-sectional shape of a thermoplastic welding rod?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triangular",
            "b) Hexagonal",
            "c) Square",
            "d) Pentagonal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A welding rod or a thermoplastic welding rod is used mainly in plastic welding. The rod should not be very porous or it may catch voids. This rod has a cross sectional shape triangular or circular. "
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of related processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soldering",
            "b) Percussion",
            "c) Brazing",
            "d) Hard-pressing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Among the following, soldering, pressing and hard-pressing are few of the types of related processes. Percussion is one of the forms of resistance welding processes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of solid state welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Projection",
            "b) Ultrasonic",
            "c) Friction",
            "d) Diffusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are various types of welding processes, one of them is a newer welding process. Under this, there are two types, one is electron-beam and another is the use of laser. "
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "What is the density of the plastic used in speed tip welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 916 kg/m3",
            "b) 923 kg/m3",
            "c) 946 kg/m3",
            "d) 982 kg/m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Among the following, ultrasonic, friction and diffusion are a few of the types of related processes. Percussion is one of the forms of resistance welding processes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Which of the following could be considered as a related process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Explosive",
            "b) Oxy-Hydrogen welding",
            "c) Oxy-Acetylene cutting",
            "d) Electron-beam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The plastic which is used in the process of speed tip welding is polypropylene or polypropene. It is classified under thermoplastics materials. The density of polypropylene is 946 kg/m3 and it starts melting at 130°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "In which run weld, in ordinary steels, the grain refinement takes place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) First",
            "b) Second",
            "c) Third",
            "d) Fourth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A multi run process causes a good amount of grain refinement. With every proceeding run weld, it normalizes its previous run. In ordinary steels, grain refinement takes place in the second run. "
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "What is the minimum strength of mild steel arc welds on addition of microelements in the slag?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 43 kgf/mm2",
            "b) 39 kgf/mm2",
            "c) 45kgf/mm2",
            "d) 48 kgf/mm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When there is an addition of some microelements in the slag along with a few materials being present which are not metals, there is an increase in the strength of the mild steel arc weld. The minimum amount of strength goes up to 43 kgf/mm2, which is 430 N/mm2. "
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "Which of the following is affected by weld contour?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fatigue",
            "b) Creep",
            "c) High pressure property",
            "d) Low pressure property"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The contour present on the welds form notches. The contours in the form of notches then affect the low temperature properties of the structure and also the fatigue properties. "
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "Thermite contains which metal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zinc",
            "b) Copper",
            "c) Aluminium",
            "d) Manganese"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reaction that takes place in between compounds and elements is known welding with solid reactants. These reaction are exothermic, that is give out heat as a product. Thermit reaction is a common example for this, which is mixture of aluminium and rust. "
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "Which of the following property is considered for controlling the porosity of the metal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid solubility",
            "b) Liquid solubility",
            "c) Gas solubility",
            "d) Flame solubility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The amount of solubility of gas in liquid or solid welded metals is considered to be an essential criteria for the control of porosity of the weld. The gas reactions which occur, then regulate porosity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "Which of the following property is responsible for weld metal cracking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stress",
            "b) Strain",
            "c) Temperature conditions",
            "d) Pressure conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Slags used in welding are generally a combination of silica materials and some carbonate compounds. In fusion welding, some amount of bead control has to be done, which is done by the slags, for this purpose, to improve its performance, microelements like manganese are added. "
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "A thermit reaction produces heat up to what temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4800°F",
            "b) 4000°F",
            "c) 5600°F",
            "d) 5300°F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The stresses which get developed in welding during shrinkage are of importance. These stresses are considered to be an important factor which are responsible for the cracking that occurs in metal welds. "
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "What is the maximum strength of mild steel arc welds on addition of microelements in the slag?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 53 kgf/mm2",
            "b) 49 kgf/mm2",
            "c) 57kgf/mm2",
            "d) 61 kgf/mm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "Which of the following types of fuel gas is commonly used in gas welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Biogas",
            "b) Coal gas",
            "c) Acetylene",
            "d) Methane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gas welding is usually referred as oxy welding or oxy-fuel welding which is a process of joining metallic materials by application of heat produced by the gas flame. In gas welding, acetylene is commonly used as fuel gas which mixed with proper proportion of oxygen in a mixing chamber of welding torch. Gas welding can produce a hot flame of temperature about 3000-3500 ⁰C."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "Oxy-acetylene process is most suited for which of the following process of joining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metal wires",
            "b) Metal sheets",
            "c) Metal tubes",
            "d) Metal bars"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Oxy-acetylene process is most suited for the joining of metal sheets or for joining metal plates which are having a thickness of 2mm to 50mm. While joining, the molten metal flows together to form a continuous joint. "
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "For what thickness of a material, in an oxy-acetylene is a welding rod used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 mm",
            "b) 15 mm",
            "c) 20 mm",
            "d) 25 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Oxy-acetylene processes are mainly used for the joining of metal sheets or for joining metal plates which are having a thickness of 2mm to 50mm. When the thickness of the material is more than 15 mm, an additional filler metal is added like a welding rod. "
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "What is the flame temperature of city gas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1500°C",
            "b) 1600°C",
            "c) 1700°C",
            "d) 1800°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: City gas is a type of fuel gas that is used for the welding of thin sheets of steel which have a thickness of up to 3 mm. The flame temperature of city gas is approximately about 1700°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "In a neutral flame, what is the temperature in the inner core?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3200°C",
            "b) 2100°C",
            "c) 1250°C",
            "d) 2700°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When equal amount of oxygen and acetylene is made to react in a torch, a neutral flame gets produced. The inner core has a temperature of 3200°C, whereas the tip of the neutral flame has a temperature of 1250°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "What is the flame temperature of water gas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2500°C",
            "b) 2800°C",
            "c) 2300°C",
            "d) 3100°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Water gas is a type of fuel gas that is used for the welding of thin sheets of steel which have a thickness of up to 8 mm. The flame temperature of water gas is approximately about 2300°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "What is the flame temperature of methane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2000°C",
            "b) 1200°C",
            "c) 2700°C",
            "d) 3300°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "What is the flame temperature of acetylene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1700°C",
            "b) 2200°C",
            "c) 2800°C",
            "d) 3200°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "What is the flame temperature of hydrogen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2000°C",
            "b) 1200°C",
            "c) 2700°C",
            "d) 3300°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A neutral flame is the one in which there is an equal amount of supply of oxygen and acetylene. A carburising flame is the one in which the supply of acetylene is much more than that of oxygen and an oxidizing flame is the one where there is ample supply of oxygen compared to acetylene. "
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "What is the order of temperature of heat produced in an electric arc furnace?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3000°C – 4000°C",
            "b) 4000°C – 5000°C",
            "c) 5000°C – 6000°C",
            "d) 6000°C – 7000°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An electric arc furnace generates a lot of heat when the working metal comes in contact with the electrode. The heat that is generated in this joining process is of the order 6000°C to 7000°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "The distance from the center of arc to the tip of electrode is called what?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arc distance",
            "b) Arc length",
            "c) Arc crater",
            "d) Arc depth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The distance from the center of the arc to the tip of the electrode, right till the bottom of the crater is defined to be the arc length. The arc length is considered to be one of the most essential variable in welding process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "What is the length of the arc generally?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1mm – 2mm",
            "b) 2mm – 3mm",
            "c) 3mm – 4mm",
            "d) 4mm – 5mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "In arc welding process, the high quality alternator functions at what frequency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 250 Hz",
            "b) 300 Hz",
            "c) 350 Hz",
            "d) 400 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In an arc welding process, there are alternators used for producing high current and function at lower frequency, and there are alternators which are of high quality and work at high frequency. The functioning frequency of these alternators is 400 Hz. "
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "Which type of electrode is designed for melting quickly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fast fill",
            "b) Fast freeze",
            "c) Quick fill",
            "d) Fill freeze"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electrodes which are classified into three types, fast fill, fast freeze and fill freeze. Among these, the fast fill electrodes are considered to be able to operate at extremely high welding speeds, and hence fast fill electrodes are designed for quick melting. "
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "What amount of electricity gets converted into heat energy in an arc welding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.25 kWh",
            "b) 0.75 kWh",
            "c) 1 kWh",
            "d) 2 kWh"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In an arc welding process, there is a direct conversion of electrical energy into heat energy. An approximate amount of 1 kilo Watt hour of electrical energy gets converted into heat energy for this process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "Which type of electrode is designed for melting quickly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fast fill",
            "b) Fast freeze",
            "c) Quick fill",
            "d) Fill freeze"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Arc welding machines are able of working on both alternating current supply as well as direct current supply. But mainly arc welding machines work on D.C. supply only, where the positive terminal is connected to the welding machine. "
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "Which material is not used as an iron coating on the electrode used in arc welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cellulose",
            "b) Iron powder",
            "c) Calcium fluoride",
            "d) Steel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electrodes which are classified into three types, fast fill, fast freeze and fill freeze. In fast freeze electrodes, a filler metal is supplied. This filler element gets solidifies and provides a variety in positions of the weld. "
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "What is the capacity of an automatic welding machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 to 200A",
            "b) 300 to 400A",
            "c) 500 to 700A",
            "d) 800 to 3000A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An automatic welding machine has a high amount of capacity. Its capacity ranges in between 800 to 300A. This type of machine is not portable and is suitably used for heavy welding processes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "What is the capacity of a light manual welding machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 to 200A",
            "b) 300 to 400A",
            "c) 500 to 700A",
            "d) 800 to 3000A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A light manual welding machine has one of the lowest capacity among all types of welding machines. Its capacity ranges in between 100 to 200A. This machine is portable and is best suited for light welding processes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "What is the current required in an Oxygen’s INDARC 400 (S) transformer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 amp to 100 amp",
            "b) 40 amp to 250 amp",
            "c) 50 amp to 400 amp",
            "d) 60 amp to 500 amp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In an Oxygen’s INDARC 400 (S) transformer, there is a hand wheel provided which is used for varying the output, for altering the air gap in the core and results in regulating the current in between 50 amperes to 400 amperes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "What is the efficiency of an A.C. welding transformer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.6",
            "b) 0.7",
            "c) 0.8",
            "d) 0.9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A.C welding is currently gaining considerable ground. The efficiency of an alternating current welding transformer varies from 0.8 to 0.85 and the efficiency of A.C. outfits is in the range of 0.3 to 0.6. "
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "What is the amount of electric energy required per kg in dc welding operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-4 kWh",
            "b) 3-7 kWh",
            "c) 4-9 kWh",
            "d) 6-10 kWh"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The amount of electrical energy consumed required per kg for a D.C. welding operation, is 6 kWh to 10 kWh. Direct current provides the advantage of distribution of the heat needed inside the arc. "
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "Which material is not used for making non-consumable electrodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon",
            "b) Graphite",
            "c) Sodium",
            "d) Tungsten"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Non-consumable electrodes, are those electrodes which do not get consumed as the welding operation proceeds. These electrodes are primarily made up of materials like carbon, graphite and tungsten. "
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "Which of the following characteristic does not define a coated electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maintenance of arc",
            "b) Protection from oxygen",
            "c) Protection from nitrogen",
            "d) Preventing other elements into molten metal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A coated electrode is a further classification of a consumable electrode. The purpose of the electrode is to maintain the arc, to shield the molten metal from oxygen and nitrogen present in the air and to provide other alloying elements into the molten metal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "What is the amount of carbon contained by a soft steel wire?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1% to 0.18%",
            "b) 0.15% to 0.22%",
            "c) 0.18% to 0.26%",
            "d) 0.2% to 0.27%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A soft steel wire contains about 0.1% to 0.18% of carbon. Soft steel wire also has other contents in it like phosphorous and sulphur in it. The amount of phosphorous is soft steel is around 0.0025%."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "What is the percentage of carbon present in low alloy steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.15%",
            "b) 0.2%",
            "c) 0.25%",
            "d) 0.3%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The amount of carbon that is present in a soft steel wire is around 0.1% to 0.18% and the amount of carbon in terms of percentage composition in low alloy steels is 0.25%."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "Why is carbon used in carbon arc welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Generation of more heat at electrode tip",
            "b) Generation of less heat at electrode tip",
            "c) Provides coating",
            "d) Fixed polarity is maintained"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Carbon is used in carbon arc welding, at the negative terminal of the cathode. The reason for employing carbon at the negative terminal is that, a lesser amount of heat is generated at the electron tip than at the workpiece. "
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "What is the temperature at the negative terminal in carbon arc welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3000°C",
            "b) 3100°C",
            "c) 3200°C",
            "d) 3300°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "The process of carbon arc welding is not used for which of the following material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Copper",
            "b) Bronze",
            "c) Aluminium",
            "d) Iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The process of carbon arc melting is widely used for copper and copper alloys, hence bronze and brass are treated by this method. Aluminium can also be treated likewise, but not iron metal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Which gas is used as a protection in carbon arc welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon dioxide",
            "b) Carbon monoxide",
            "c) Carbon tetra fluoride",
            "d) Methane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In carbon arc welding, there has to be a protection to be provided to the molten weld. This protection is provided in the form of an envelope by using a long arc giving carbon monoxide gas. "
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "What is the temperature at the positive terminal in carbon arc welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3800°C",
            "b) 3900°C",
            "c) 4000°C",
            "d) 4100°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Carbon is used in carbon arc welding, at the negative terminal of the cathode and the metal which is being worked upon functions as the positive terminal. The temperature of the electrode at the positive terminal is 3900°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "What is the temperature of the negative electrode in metal arc welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2200°C",
            "b) 2300°C",
            "c) 2400°C",
            "d) 2500°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In metal arc welding, the temperature of negative electrode is higher than the temperature of positive electrode. The temperature produced in a negative electrode of a metal arc weld is about 2400°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "What is the temperature of the positive electrode in metal arc welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2300°C",
            "b) 2400°C",
            "c) 2500°C",
            "d) 2600°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "Which bead character is seen due to too high welding current?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pilling of metal",
            "b) Pilling of weld metal",
            "c) Excess splatter",
            "d) Small bead formation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: On provision of too low current, there is pilling of metal seen. When the voltage provided is very high, beads formed are too high. When the speed of weld is less, pilling of weld metal takes place and when welding currents are too high, excessive splatter formation occurs. "
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "Which kind of resistance is experienced in upset butt welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electric resistance",
            "b) Magnetic resistance",
            "c) Thermal resistance",
            "d) Air resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the making of an upset butt welding, there are jaws made of copper, into which the part to be welded is put, and hence a solid contact is made. At this point of contact, while the current flows, it gets transformed into heat because of electric resistance. "
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be easily be welded from flash butt welding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tin",
            "b) Lead",
            "c) Cast irons",
            "d) Carbon steel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In flash butt welding process, the welding of materials like steels and other iron alloys are easy to weld, except for cast iron. The welding of materials like tin, lead, zinc and antimony cannot be welded using flash butt method. "
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "Electrodes used in spot welding are made up of which material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only Copper",
            "b) Copper and tungsten",
            "c) Copper and chromium",
            "d) Copper and aluminium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The electrodes that are employed in the spot welding are required to possess a high amount of electrical and thermal conductivity. Hence, they are primarily made up of copper or copper and tungsten or copper and chromium. "
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "How are the metals to be welded connected to each other in spot welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electric contact",
            "b) Magnetic field",
            "c) Mechanical pressure",
            "d) Direct contact"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In spot welding process, the metal or the alloy parts which are to be welded, are heated in their in their zones. To bring these parts in contact with one another, mechanical pressure is applied, causing them to connect. "
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is not used in applying pressure in spot welding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hand lever",
            "b) Foot lever",
            "c) Air pressure",
            "d) Hydraulic cylinder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "Up to what thickness, can steel be welded using spot welding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 mm",
            "b) 11 mm",
            "c) 12 mm",
            "d) 13 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In spot welding process, to bring the heated parts in contact with one another, mechanical pressure is applied. This pressure can be of three types, by using foot lever, by providing air pressure or by using a hydraulic cylinder. The use of these methods allows steel or other metal parts to be welded up to a thickness of 12 mm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "What is the maximum power supply needed for the working of spot welding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 135 kVA",
            "b) 140 kVA",
            "c) 145 kVA",
            "d) 150 kVA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Spot welding can be used for all types of ductile metals. It can also be employed for structures of sheet metals, and can be applied for making of boxes and cans. For its applications, the maximum power that can be needed for this process is 150 kVA. "
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "What is the minimum power supply needed for the working of spot welding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 kVA",
            "b) 14 kVA",
            "c) 6 kVA",
            "d) 22 kVA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "In an iron thermit, how many moles of aluminium reacts with three moles of iron oxide to give nine moles of iron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 7",
            "c) 8",
            "d) 9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The thermit process, which is used for welding depends on the chemical reaction between oxide of iron and aluminium metal. According to this reaction, when 8 moles of aluminium reacts with 3 moles of iron oxide, then, 4 moles of aluminium oxide and 9 moles of iron is formed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "What is the magnitude of temperature produced in a thermit reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2500°C",
            "b) 3000°C",
            "c) 3500°C",
            "d) 4000°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Around the parts which are to be united, superheated liquid steel is poured, which then effects in forming the weld. This process, hence, is a fusion welding process. The part represented by the question mark is the crucible. "
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "At what temperature, does fusion welding takes place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 850°C",
            "b) 900°C",
            "c) 950°C",
            "d) 1000°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The process of fusion welding can be used for joining metal to a metal or a metal can be joined to a ceramic. For the joining of this process, a temperature of 900°C is provided for the approach. "
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of diffusion welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gas-pressure welding",
            "b) Vacuum fusion welding",
            "c) Eutectic fusion bonding",
            "d) Eutectoid fusion welding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Diffusion welding is has three basic techniques which are incorporated by it. These three basic techniques are, gas – pressure welding, vacuum fusion welding and eutectic fusion welding. "
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "What is the minimum frequency used in ultrasonic welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10,000 Hz",
            "b) 20,000 Hz",
            "c) 30,000 Hz",
            "d) 40,000 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The process of ultrasonic welding is mainly used for the joining of similar metals or dissimilar metals using vibration energy, by way of high frequency. The minimum frequency needed for this purpose is 20,000 Hz. "
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "What is the maximum frequency used in ultrasonic welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30,000 Hz",
            "b) 40,000 Hz",
            "c) 50,000 Hz",
            "d) 60,000 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "In what conditions are the parts kept before welding in ultrasonic welding method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low static pressure",
            "b) High static pressure",
            "c) Low moving pressure",
            "d) High moving pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In ultrasonic welding method, the parts which are to be joined, are kept clamping to one another in between of supporting member and the welding tip. This clamping is done at a low static pressure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "What is the maximum thickness that can be welded in ultrasonic welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.8 mm",
            "b) 2.1 mm",
            "c) 2.3 mm",
            "d) 2.5 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Weldings such as spot welding or continuous seam welding can be done through ultrasonic welding. The maximum thickness that can be achieved varies depending on the metal. The maximum thickness can be that can be welded is 2.5mm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "What is the minimum thickness that can be welded in ultrasonic welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.58 mm",
            "b) 0.21 mm",
            "c) 0.38 mm",
            "d) 0.92 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In ultrasonic welding method, the parts which are to be joined, are kept clamping to one another in between of supporting member and the welding tip. In doing this, no current is required to be passed through the metal, and usually, no heat is needed for this too. "
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a factor for explosive welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High relative velocity",
            "b) Less amount of plastics",
            "c) Proper orientation",
            "d) High pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "Which gas is used for the removal of oxygen layer formed on molten iron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrogen",
            "b) Oxygen",
            "c) Carbon dioxide",
            "d) Chlorine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In oxygen cutting method, under considerable amount of pressure, when a jet of oxygen gas is made to blow on the particles of molten iron oxide, the oxygen layer present on the molten iron gets removed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "Up to what amount of carbon content in steels, can they be treated by oxygen cutting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.3%",
            "b) 0.2%",
            "c) 0.7%",
            "d) 0.4%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For a steel to be treated by oxygen cutting process, the carbon content that should be available in terms of percentage composition is around 0.7%, that is, the steel that can be treated by this process is a high alloy steel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "Up to what temperatures are high alloy steels heated before treating them by oxygen cutting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 675°C",
            "b) 725°C",
            "c) 775°C",
            "d) 825°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In oxygen cutting process, not all steels can be treated by this method. Only high alloy steels can be treated by this method. These steels need to be preheated before oxygen cutting. The temperature range up to which these steels are preheated is about 650°C to 700°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "What are the number of opening available in the cutting torch used in oxygen cutting process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Just like any other gas welding equipment, the welding torch gets substituted by a cutting torch in oxygen cutting process. The total number of openings available in the torch are six, with a large opening at the center, making the count to seven. "
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "What is the maximum oxygen pressure that can be applied to steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 13 atm",
            "b) 14 atm",
            "c) 15 atm",
            "d) 16 atm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "What is the minimum oxygen pressure that can be applied to steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 atm",
            "b) 4 atm",
            "c) 5 atm",
            "d) 6 atm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In oxygen cutting process, not all steels can be treated by this method. Only high alloy steels can be treated by this method. The pressure supply of oxygen should not be low, as it may lead to the formation of slag on the bottom of the cut. The minimum oxygen pressure that can be applied to steels is 3 atmospheres or 300 kN/m2. "
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "What is the initial oxygen pressure provided through the lance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 atm to 2 atm",
            "b) 2 atm to 3 atm",
            "c) 3 atm to 4 atm",
            "d) 4 atm to 5 atm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In oxygen lance cutting, jet of oxygen is passed through steel pipes, and by doing this, holes are produced. For doing this, the jet of oxygen is passed through the lancer under the pressure of 1 atm to 2 atm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "What should the outer diameter of a thick-welled lance be, for having good results?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 13 mm to 15 mm",
            "b) 15 mm to 17 mm",
            "c) 17 mm to 19 mm",
            "d) 19 mm to 21 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In oxygen lance cutting, when the lance is made up of a thick wall, with its outer diameter of 17 mm to 19 mm, and possessing an inner diameter of 8 mm to 6 mm, respectively, then good results can be obtained. "
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods cannot be used for welding carbon steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arc welding",
            "b) Gas welding",
            "c) Ultrasonic welding",
            "d) Forge welding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the welding of carbon steel material, one may use the arc welding method. To gas weld carbon steel is also a feasible option and carbon steels can be treated using forge welding also, but it cannot be welded using ultrasonic welding. "
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "High alloys steels are preheated up to what temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 350°C",
            "b) 400°C",
            "c) 450°C",
            "d) 500°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: High alloy steels are those steels which contain high amount of carbon in them. These alloys need to be preheated before welding in order to avoid cracking. The temperature up to which these alloys are preheated is 400°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "Up to what percent of carbon content in steel, it is not required to preheat it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.25% – 0.3%",
            "b) 0.3% – 0.35%",
            "c) 0.35% – 0.4%",
            "d) 0.4% – 0.45%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Low carbon steels are the ones containing low amount of carbon in them, which does not require preheating. The amount of carbon content needed in low carbon steels, is 0.25% to 0.3%, if preheating is to be avoided. "
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "Which of the following material is not used in alloy steels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Molybdenum",
            "b) Nickel",
            "c) Chromium",
            "d) Sodium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In alloy steels, there is a big composition used up by iron. Along with iron, there vitally has to be carbon in alloy steels. Along with carbon, there is a presence of other elements such as, molybdenum, nickel and chromium in small amounts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "Which among the following methods is best suited for stainless steels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electric butt welding",
            "b) Seam welding",
            "c) Flux coated arc welding",
            "d) Oxy-hydrogen welding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are a few methods of treating stainless steels for welding, such as, any of the metal arc welding methods or the oxy-acetylene welding method, but the one best suited for this alloy is electric butt welding. "
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "Stainless steels are annealed at what temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 650°C – 700°C",
            "b) 700°C – 750°C",
            "c) 750°C – 800°C",
            "d) 800°C – 850°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Stainless steels are hardened by constant heating and cooling and the best method suited for this alloy is electric butt welding. As soon as the stainless steel alloy is electric butt welded, it needs to be annealed at a temperature in between 750°C to 800°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a material used for making an electrode in metal arc welding, for treating stainless steels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Niobium",
            "b) Columbium",
            "c) Titanium",
            "d) Potassium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stainless steels are best welded using the electric butt welding method and then followed by annealing at around 750°C to 800°C. Stainless steels can also be welded using the metal arc welding methods. For this the electrode which is needed is made up of niobium, titanium and columbium. These materials avoid the occurrence of the defect called weld decay. "
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "What is the temperature needed for preheating in cast irons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 550°C",
            "b) 600°C",
            "c) 650°C",
            "d) 700°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cast irons, upon the removal of welding heat, get solidified very quickly. This solidification takes place due to the surrounding cold mass and the air around. Because of such quick cooling, the carbon gets retained and hard metal stays in the weld. To overcome this, cast irons have to be preheated to 600°C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "Which of the following articles is not manufactured using riveting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rail wagons",
            "b) Coaches",
            "c) Pressure vessels",
            "d) Helmets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Riveting is largely used in the manufacture of rail wagons, coaches, pressure vessels, bridges and few types of furnace bodies, but for the manufacture of helmets, riveting cannot be used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials is not used in making rivets?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wrought iron",
            "b) Mild steel",
            "c) Brass",
            "d) Calcium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Riveting is a process that is used for fastening a particular joint permanently. The following figure is that of a Cup head riveting or snap head riveting is the most commonly used method of riveting. "
    }
]